<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://www.theexclusive.org//feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-08-05T17:07:53-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org///</id><title type="html">The Exclusive Or</title><subtitle>On academic, expatriate, and other unusual forms of life.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ill-Judged Britishness, and Self-Deprecation within a Power Dynamic</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/08/deprecation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ill-Judged Britishness, and Self-Deprecation within a Power Dynamic" /><published>2018-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/08/deprecation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/08/deprecation.html">&lt;p&gt;I really should know better. Twice now, I’ve done this to myself.
I was a social event with one of my PhD students,
like a party during a conference, where I was introducing
them to a colleague. Feeling relaxed after a beer
or two, I attempted an ill-judged joke, “So-and-so has
the misfortune of being one of my students.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often that type of humour works well for me,
and is enjoyed all around. Well, maybe I’m not perceptive
enough to tell if anyone else enjoys it, but I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misfortunate joke never works, though. Both times the student turned
and looked at me like I had three heads.
Why would I say something like that about myself? Why would
being my PhD student be a bad thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second time this happened, I at least maintained
enough poise to explain myself. “Nothing to worry about,” I said quietly
to my student. “I’m just feeling a bit British.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Self-deprecation,” I said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, of course.” Immediate understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="attempts at social interaction" /><category term="anecdotes" /><category term="expat" /><summary type="html">I really should know better. Twice now, I’ve done this to myself.
I was a social event with one of my PhD students,
like a party during a conference, where I was introducing
them to a colleague. Feeling relaxed after a beer
or two, I attempted an ill-judged joke, “So-and-so has
the misfortune of being one of my students.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part IV&amp;amp;#58 A Tsunami of Logistics</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/07/logistic-tsunami.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part IV&amp;#58 A Tsunami of Logistics" /><published>2018-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/07/logistic-tsunami</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/07/logistic-tsunami.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fourth in a tidal wave of posts about
&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/stress%20in%20research&quot;&gt;stress in research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a source of stress for people who have gotten a bit more senior
in their careers, like new professors or managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a previous post in the series, a colleague commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What gets me is the daily tsunami of logistics: questions that need responses,
decisions that have to be made, scheduling, and millions of small deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every new professor mentions this. If senior professors complain about this
less often, perhaps it is because they are simply better at ignoring questions
that need responses. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making decisions is stressful for those who lack the training or personality.
A PhD trains you to think deeply and carefully about an issue.
Scientifically speaking, you want to reserve judgment when you don’t have all of
the information, not go ahead and make a snap decision anyway.
As an administrator, though, sometimes that is exactly what you must do.
Maybe the thing that stresses me the most, though, is when I inevitably fall
behind the tsunami, I hate the feeling that I’m letting people down.
This feeling is actually one of the things that bothers me most about
academia, even though I’m well aware that if I did spend all of my
time attending to logistics promptly, I would still be letting people down,
in a deeper way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics tsunami is, like all tsunamis, perilous. The obvious danger
is that you spend so much time sending emails
&lt;a href=&quot;http://theoatmeal.com/comics/email_monster&quot;&gt;like a tired diplomat&lt;/a&gt;
that you lose your time for work that requires deeper thought.
Your ability to do deep work is why you won your job in the first place,
so not doing it once you’ve reached a higher level is not so great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics tsunami brings another, more insidious danger.
This danger is not about losing
your time but losing your mind. Your unconscious mind, I mean.
A lot of our most important thinking happens unconsciously,
our brains churning in the background while our focus is elsewhere,
until the wonderful moment when a thought finally pops into our consciousness,
like Athena in the mind of Zeus.
For me, this usually happens when I’m walking.
For you, it might be in the shower, or when you are sitting with your coffee.
I really like the way that Female Science Professor talks about
&lt;a href=&quot;http://science-professor.blogspot.com/2014/11/this-is-your-brain-on-administration.html&quot;&gt;your brain on administration&lt;/a&gt;.
When you start doing too much administration, the tsunami starts to take
over your unconscious mind, and the wonderful ideas that pop up start to be
about what you can spend a tiny slice of your grant budget on, or
how to phrase that sensitive email, instead of what to write your
next paper about. This is the most terrible danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now delayed for too long the part of the blog where I explain my
optimistic but wise, surprising but helpful, advice on how
to manage the tsunami. I am afraid that I must report that
the delay didn’t help me come up with any better ideas.
All I can say is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you have many decisions, you must decide quickly.&lt;/em&gt; This is the secret
that good decider-people know that you and I don’t. Me, I like to mull over
things. Then by the time I actually make a decision, I know I’m sure,
so I feel a lot better about it. That’s OK for big decisions, but not so good
for deciding whether you want to meet tomorrow at 1pm or 2pm.
When it doesn’t really matter, wrap up the matter quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learn how to partition your time.&lt;/em&gt; Deep thinking requires uninterrupted
blocks of time. These are hard to find, but you must.
I think that the optimal block size varies from person
to person. Some people split things up by day.
You could have “teaching days”, “admin days”, “research days”, and so on.
Some people enforce no-meeting days. Some people will work Sundays,
but only on research.
Some people don’t check email before 4PM.
Some people send lots of emails late at night because they’re tired anyway.
I don’t split things up by day, because I like to do small tasks
when I get tired from concentrating. I make sure to schedule meetings back
to back, to try to keep blocks of time for deeper work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protect the time when you are most creative.&lt;/em&gt; When you go to partition
your time, you’ll want to remember what time of day you are most creative
and have the most energy. That is the time that you need to reserve for
the most creative work. If people often drop by your office — we all love
an open door policy — then this is the time to not &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; in your
office.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Make good use of odd chunks of time.&lt;/em&gt; As much as we bemoan smartphones,
they shine at this. If you only have 10 minutes until your next meeting,
the tsunami will happily offer you things that take only 10 minutes to do.
To be an effective professor, you need to play Tetris with time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need a to-do list.&lt;/em&gt; If you know about things you need to do
that aren’t written down, a part of your unconscious will repeat them over
and over, so you don’t forget. You have many more important jobs for
your unconscious mind than that. I like the principles behind the
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/11/gtd-made-simple-why-i-think-internet.html&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done system&lt;/a&gt;
very much, although my practice is distinctly imperfect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find a fast way to schedule meetings.&lt;/em&gt; Really a special case of the first
principle. If you spend 20 hours a week in meetings, it’s easy to spend
a couple hours a week arranging meetings. You need to make arranging a time
as simple as possible, using whatever tools work for you. For example,
I have my Google calendar hooked up to Doodle, so when an administrator
sends out a Doodle poll, I can respond in one click. Some online calendars
have features for creating appointment slots. Some people publish their
free/busy schedule publicly. Whatever works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Know when “good enough” is good enough.&lt;/em&gt; The easiest way to get more things
done is to spend less time doing each thing. Your research requires certain
habits of mind, careful and precise thought, perhaps. I guarantee you that
this level of clarity and precision is not required for your emails.
Jenny Pickerill has a nice
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JennyPickerill/status/985780112112091141&quot;&gt;Twitter thread on satisficing&lt;/a&gt;
as a professor.
Satisficing is more painful for tasks that are more central
to our mission. Any university class can be made 20% better at the cost
of twice as much prep time — don’t do it. (I received this advice,
second hand, from an award-winning lecturer!) I’m not saying that
you should be puzzling out your colleague’s slides for the first time
in front of the class, either. You need to find something in the middle,
and the same goes for the service that you do inside and outside
of the university.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><summary type="html">The fourth in a tidal wave of posts about
stress in research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Social Skills in Context, or How being a Professor is Kind of Like Being a Mafia Hitman</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/06/mafia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Skills in Context, or How being a Professor is Kind of Like Being a Mafia Hitman" /><published>2018-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/06/mafia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/06/mafia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Ruggiero&quot;&gt;Benjamin “Lefty Guns” Ruggiero&lt;/a&gt;
was a fearsome Mafia hitman in New York in the 70s.
According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_D._Pistone&quot;&gt;an undercover FBI agent&lt;/a&gt;
who knew him well, he was smart and savvy in underworld situations.
He could walk into a restaurant where he knew no one,
watch who talked to who, watch how they talked,
and work out who was in the underworld, who received more deference,
whether the restaurant was being extorted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other situations, a different story. The FBI agent,
Joseph Pistone, was himself an incredibly perceptive observer
(if he wasn’t, he’d have been murdered). He reports:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A lot of these wiseguys did not have the ability to move around the country.
Once you got these guys out of New York City, they were like fish out of water....
As they schooled me in the mafia, I had to school them on how to make airline reservations.
I am talking about a 49-year-old man,
telling him how to make airline reservations to three different cities, with an
open return, because we
did not know what date we were going to return to New York City.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&quot;quote-source&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;quote-author&quot;&gt;Joseph Pistone&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;cite class=&quot;quote-title&quot;&gt;Donnie Brasco: My Undercover Life in the Mafia&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I was immediately reminded of computer science research.
In research situations, I think of myself as reasonably socially aware:
I have a network of mentors, students, and collaborators;
I can meet new colleagues and have interesting technical discussions;
I can even navigate the occasional difficult conversation when the need
arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But outside of work, I can be a bit more awkward,
or at least that’s what my wife says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stereotype technical people as having low social skills, and
I’ll admit knowing people who fully meet that stereotype.
The Mafia hitman reminds us that social skills are context specific:
you can be savvy in one type of situation, and clueless in another.
“Social skills” aren’t a single skill, any more than intellectual
skills are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the term implies something else. Social skills are skills.
You can learn them.
And it is in the interests of your career to do so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="social skills" /><category term="painfully extended metaphors" /><summary type="html">Benjamin “Lefty Guns” Ruggiero
was a fearsome Mafia hitman in New York in the 70s.
According to an undercover FBI agent
who knew him well, he was smart and savvy in underworld situations.
He could walk into a restaurant where he knew no one,
watch who talked to who, watch how they talked,
and work out who was in the underworld, who received more deference,
whether the restaurant was being extorted.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part III&amp;amp;#58 The Trouble about Freedom</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/05/freedom.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part III&amp;#58 The Trouble about Freedom" /><published>2018-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/05/freedom</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/05/freedom.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The third post in what is becoming an increasingly long
series on &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/stress%20in%20research&quot;&gt;stress in research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joked before that there’s no reason researchers should feel stress:
how stressful can a job be if you’re not expected to roll in to work until 10
o’clock in the morning? But more seriously, this
flexibility is itself a source of stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academics don’t really have bosses, despite what our
senior leadership sometimes seem to think. We do have a head
of department, of course, but the relationship isn’t
like having a supervisor. I don’t have weekly meetings
with my department head to report my progress on my current
projects. And I would &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; go to my head of department and say I’ve got too much to do, can she tell me
how I should prioritize my workload so that I focus on tasks
that are most important to the University.
The very idea is laughable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of having a boss, we have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgbovine.net/why-academics-feel-overworked.htm&quot;&gt;sources of work&lt;/a&gt;. Students from our own university and around the world ask us if we
can supervise their research projects. We
review and comment on reports from our own students.
We are asked to evaluate finished PhD theses from students
at other universities, in our own country
and worldwide.
 Funding agencies from our country and others ask
us to review proposals for multi-million pound research projects.
Representatives from the government ask us
to discuss connections with problems of national interest.
We organize workshops and conferences.
We meet researchers in other universities and governments
to learn about their work and explore potential collaborations.
The great thing about the blog I just linked to
— it is actually called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgbovine.net/why-academics-feel-overworked.htm&quot;&gt;why academics feel overworked&lt;/a&gt; — is that it tries to make a complete
list of where academic work comes from.
My list just above is incomplete
because I’m only mentioning things that I can remember
happening in the past week. (And this, with me
 on sabbatical;
I’m not teaching this year.)
All of these sources of work are people who are asking
politely for our help on important work of their own.
None of these sources of work know about each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be successful, of course it is important to learn to say “no”, and to learn to say “no” often.
There are tricks about how to say “no” better, in a way
that helps the person who have asked. Many other blogs
talk about that, so I won’t go further now.
It’s enough to say that even if you say “no” a lot,
you will still have a lot to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I want to talk about flexibility.
It’s no surprise that having a lot to do creates stress.
But having the flexibility to choose what to do
also creates stress.
The problem is that flexibility creates guilt.
Suppose I have tasks A, B, C, and D to do — too many — and
my boss instructs me to prioritize C, even though I think A
is more important. I might be annoyed or dismayed
by a poor decision being made, but I’m not &lt;em&gt;responsible&lt;/em&gt;
for the poor decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; prioritize, I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; responsible.
When I choose to do one thing, I’m keenly aware
that there are many other things that I could be doing,
behind each a person who would like a few minutes
(or a few hours) of my help. For every thing I choose to do,
there are other people that I feel like I am letting down.
I am never quite
sure if the thing I have chosen to do is the right one.
Sometimes I’m quite sure that the thing that I’m doing
is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the most important, but maybe simply the most
important that I have enough energy for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the flexibility necessary?
Why couldn’t academic work and research work be managed
more directly, like other types of work?
Our situation is not as unusual as it may seem —
in any career, the more senior you become, the more
you are expected to set the agenda rather than follow an
agenda that is given to you. In academia and research specifically, there are
two forces that mandate flexibility for good work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first: If you do not have freedom to prioritize,
you do not have intellectual freedom, because part of intellectual
freedom is deciding what to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second: The job
of a researcher is about creating positive externalities.
Our work is to perpetuate and create a large portion
of human knowledge. When we succeed, the value of our work is enjoyed
by society as a whole, rather than the institution
that employs us. This is why the idea of going to my department
head for advice on prioritizing is so laughable.
We cannot ask the institution what is most valuable, because so much of the
value that we create does not return to the institution.
You become an academic because you believe the specialized
knowledge that fascinates you has, in some small sense,
importance to society as a whole. Another responsibility,
and another stressor!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><summary type="html">The third post in what is becoming an increasingly long
series on stress in research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part II&amp;amp;#58 Research Worth and Self-Worth</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/04/worth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part II&amp;#58 Research Worth and Self-Worth" /><published>2018-04-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/04/worth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/04/worth.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The second post in what is perhaps a
&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/stress%20in%20research&quot;&gt;series on stress in research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be surprising, but one of the main sources of stress in research is self-esteem.
It’s so common and tempting to think of career success as a measure of one’s moral worth as a person. Stated so bluntly, it sounds like the silliest thing in the world to believe, yet I expect that we have all, at least at times, at least unconsciously, fallen into this trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source of this trap is cognitive dissonance, and the danger of the trap is that research is a roller coaster. Every researcher has days when they’ve had some good success, and they feel on top of the world. To resolve the cognitive dissonance, you feel that because you’re happy about one thing, you’re happy about everything. Your career is going well, your personal life is going well, you’re just a good person all around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you know what they say about what goes up. There will always be weeks and months when experiments don’t work, when paper submissions and job applications are rejected, several in a row. Then the emotional effects can hit hard. Nobody likes having a frustrating time in their research. But if you conflate research worth with self-worth, if you tell yourself that the main way that your life will contribute to the world is by your groundbreaking work, then when your research is going poorly, you feel like a failure in life. Not for nothing has it been observed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/news/academics-face-higher-mental-health-risk-than-other-professions&quot;&gt;that academics face relatively high mental health risk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we avoid the trap of conflating your colleagues’ respect for you as a researcher with your own self-respect as a human being? For what it’s worth, I’d expect that this trap occurs in all of the creative professions. Indeed, as much as academics like to think of ourselves as unique creatures, none of the sources of stress in research are unique to the job of research. Perhaps that is a topic for another time, but it does not help us here: Knowing that our stress is shared is not alone enough to relieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another blog might tell you: Keep a professional distance. The way to  avoid conflating your research success to your self-worth is to think of research as a job rather than a calling. But that’s not the advice that I will give, because if you want to do good work, sometimes you need
to take things personally. As the great Captain says, sometimes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WLzJAebfEIg&quot;&gt;you need your pain&lt;/a&gt;. So I’ll ask the question differently.
How do we keep our passion for research without harming our mental health?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mental tricks that work a bit for me, may not work for you. So I’ll list a
few different mental strategies, strategies for self-talk — those who know me
will know that I am a big fan of talking to myself — that you can experiment with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One strategy is to focus on the fun, for example, by treating a tenure-track faculty job &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/the-awesomest-7-year-postdoc-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-the-tenure-track-faculty-life/&quot;&gt;like a seven-year postdoc&lt;/a&gt;. Richard Feynman has a wonderful story about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.physics.ohio-state.edu/~kilcup/262/feynman.html&quot;&gt;recapturing fun in his research&lt;/a&gt;. One always wonders if Feynman’s stories are exaggerated, but the principle of countering stress by fun is surely sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another good strategy is to have backup sources of self-worth. Academic jobs are naturally set up this way. Even if no one reads my papers the minute after I die, or frankly, the minute after they’re written, I’ve still taught hundreds of students about fundamental knowledge that has helped them, if only a little. That’s another source of professional self-worth. Or of course, one can seek self-worth from being a good child, parent, spouse, sibling, and friend. Both of these — teaching and family — are instances of a more general point. &lt;em&gt;We should find worth in our relationships with other people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another strategy is simply to have truly excessive reserves of self-confidence, so that whenever the roller coaster goes down, you can tell yourself with absolute conviction that the roller coaster will go up again, because by god you are brilliant enough to push it up again all by yourself. I know I’m making this sound ridiculous, but I’ve read an interview with a Nobelist who basically said that lots of other people doubted him, but he never doubted himself. Whether it was bravado or truth I don’t know, but hey, if it works for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final strategy of which I’m personally fond. I firmly believe that one of the most important mental
abilities in life, one that to the great detriment of our world few people master, is to learn to believe contradictory things. One of the many lovely details of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Kingkiller_Chronicle&quot;&gt;the Kingkiller Chronicles&lt;/a&gt;
is that there is a type of magic that depends on &lt;a href=&quot;http://kingkiller.wikia.com/wiki/Sympathy&quot;&gt;having a will strong
enough to believe contradictory things simultaneously&lt;/a&gt;.
Back in this world, almost all statements
are sometimes true and sometimes false. The same is true in research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of embracing a noble contradiction: I do believe that, if you want to be
effective as a researcher, work needs to be the most important thing to you
&lt;em&gt;during the time that you are working&lt;/em&gt;.
Creative work really does require complete focus. But there is no need
to maintain this belief while you are not working. During those times, you can understand
that most research work comes to nothing, and that is no waste as long as some
small fraction of the research in the world makes a large enough difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example: Because our careers require so much time and passion, it’s natural that professional colleagues sometimes become personal friends. This means that  I think it’s important to be able to value someone as a friend, even if you do not particularly care for their research.
Stated plainly, this is obvious — how could it be otherwise? — but it’s so
easy to be confused into thinking that once you admire one aspect of someone,
that you like everything about them.
Again, this is a confusion that arises from cognitive dissonance.
It requires conscious effort to be able to separate your admiration or criticism of someone’s work with your admiration (or lack thereof!) of them as a trustworthy, loyal friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I’ve learned to do that, perhaps I can extend the same courtesy to myself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><summary type="html">The second post in what is perhaps a
series on stress in research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part I: The Tournament and the Axe</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/03/tournament-axe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part I&amp;#58; The Tournament and the Axe" /><published>2018-03-03T04:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T04:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/03/tournament-axe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/03/tournament-axe.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Perhaps the first post in a series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From one point of view, research is the best job in the world. You get to be creative and follow your curiosity. You are always learning; if you ever stop, you have stopped doing research. You can collaborate with brilliant people, and help young smart people to find the frontiers of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for all that, I think research will never stop causing me heartache and stress. If you have any capacity in your psyche for self-doubt, you will find that capacity nurtured and magnified during your career in research. But why should this be? The requirements of the job are blessedly open-ended, and we are granted substantial flexibility in how we manage our work. I mean, come on, how stressful can a job be if you’re not expected to roll in to work until 10 o’clock in the morning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series, I will try to isolate and understand the sources of stress and in research, and how we might cope. I say “isolate”, “cope”, and not “eliminate” — I suspect that top-quality work is not possible without accepting some stress. But maybe there’s a way to get by accepting a little bit less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first triggers of stress that I want to talk about arise as a consequence of how people get jobs in research, and how the research community is structured. These are the Tournament and the Axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the Tournament. The research community is structured around an series of increasingly more selective, and more difficult, international tournaments. Most undergraduate students choose to focus their work elsewhere, but of those that choose to do a PhD, most — including your humble author — are not admitted to their first-choice school. Of those who start a PhD,
many do not complete it. Of those who complete their PhD, many do not go on to another research position.
Of those who become assistant professors in the US, some do not receive tenure.
Finally, even of the top researchers, those who have a large group and regularly
publish well-received papers, only a small number of them can honestly say that
they have ever in their career achieved a groundbreaking new result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now let’s consider your competition in the Tournament, your international colleagues in the research community. When you first join a research community, usually by attending your first workshop or conference, it’s overwhelming to meet so many new interesting people, who are fascinated by the same arcane technology as you, &lt;em&gt;and who all seem smarter than you&lt;/em&gt;. This is partly an illusion: all these people have been around the community longer than you, so they simply have more background and experience, not more raw power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s truth in the illusion too: &lt;em&gt;There really are lots of people smarter than you&lt;/em&gt;. That is no insult. I’ll explain. For the sake of argument, let’s suppose that you are a unique genius, a special talent, one in a million. Even if you are one in a million, that means there are
7600 people in the world who are smarter than you. And the organizations of the research community are
 specifically designed to help you to meet them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, the outcome of the Tournament is public. The papers we publish, the prestigious jobs that we accept, the awards that we win, these are all public. The people stronger than you, or luckier, you can see the evidence of their success. And you suspect that others, your colleagues and friends, can see where you stand as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, the Axe. Many levels of the Tournament are up or out. You either succeed in a competition to move the next level, or you move to a career outside of research. The tenure system for assistant professors in the United States is famously up or out, but all earlier levels of your career path are, too. For example, I thought being a postdoctoral researcher was the best job in the world. I loved coming in to work every day. But I also knew there was the Axe over my head. If I hadn’t made enough progress in the two years that I had, I might not be able to remain in a research active position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this together causes a lot of stress, or at least it has for me. I like to think that there are attitudes and habits of mind that can reduce the stress of the Tournament, at least a little bit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand that every Tournament is also a game. Success in the Tournament is not solely a reflection of your intelligence or your skill, but also your ability to play. It’s so easy to conflate your success in your career with your self-worth, but to do so too strongly is destructive. Disconnect your self-worth and your regard for others from performance in the Tournament.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Appreciate that winning the Tournament is not always the right move. The trap of the Tournament is that because it is a game, we naturally feel that winning a game is better than losing it. Not so. Choosing to leave a game is better than winning, when the game is not worth playing — when you enjoy other careers more than research, or if another career provides a better path for you to contribute professionally to the world. It would be almost a cliche to say “there is no shame” in leaving research, but it would also be a grave disservice, the language already buying into the bogus narrative that the competitions are there to be won. So I say instead: To start down one career path, recognize that it is not the best way for you to contribute, and choose another — I salute
and admire the strength and self-knowledge that is needed to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Tournament is not the core of research. I’ve been describing the research community as a competitive, perhaps even unfriendly, place. And it is competitive. But I’ve not found it to be unfriendly. I’ve met so many colleagues who have helped me by collaborating with me, explaining their work, graciously helping me to understand the field better. This creates the cognitive dissonance, how can the community be both competitive and helpful at the same time? I reconcile these views by &lt;em&gt;viewing competition as a type of collaboration&lt;/em&gt;. We have, together, decided to build a competition for attention, in the hope that it will help all of us to reach our full potential and teach each other as much as we can. So it is not the competition that is central to research, but  learning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To paraphrase the philosopher &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0110912/quotes/qt0447139&quot;&gt;Marsellus Wallace&lt;/a&gt;, jealously only hurts. It never helps. You meet someone smarter than you, someone who has accomplished more than you
despite being ten years younger, it’s all right to be impressed or amazed, but not jealous.
You need to train yourself to think instead: hey, what a great person to learn from!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accept the existence of the Axe. Perhaps not helpful advice, because it is too easily said, but still important. There is nothing to be gained by spending too much time staring at the Axe above you. You know it’s there and you know it’s sharp. You still need to get on with what you have to do, if you intend to stay in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><summary type="html">Perhaps the first post in a series.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travel a lot? Here’s how to stay organized, like professors do</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/12/travel-professor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travel a lot? Here's how to stay organized, like professors do" /><published>2017-12-02T09:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-02T09:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/12/travel-professor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/12/travel-professor.html">&lt;p&gt;We had a fun time on the professors’ Facebook the other day, swapping stories of the dumbest travel mistakes that we’ve made. You know, booking flights to the wrong country, forgetting to book a hotel, registering for the conference twice, and other such hilarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s face it, professors travel a lot. We are also very bad at remembering things. This is a combination that makes for comedy, unless you’re the poor sod who has to live through it. (That’s &lt;em&gt;Professor&lt;/em&gt; Sod, to you.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is, from long and painful experience, I’ve learned how to not to forget things as often when I travel. And now I will tell you my secrets, if I can remember them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep a &lt;em&gt;packing list&lt;/em&gt; (shocker!) that I reuse every time I pack my bags. I have a master list that I keep electronically and make a copy of for each trip. The important part is: Every time I arrive somewhere and forget something (toothpaste, underwear, etc), I add it to the master packing list for next time. After many years of this, I am now convinced that this list now contains everything I could possibly want to bring, and now I will never forget to pack something ever again. Well, hardly ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For toiletries I have an additional system, as they are too easy to forget. I keep a separate complete set of toiletries in a drawer, for travelling only. When I pack, I just unload the drawer into my luggage, and I know I have everything. When I return, I return the toiletries to the drawer, checking to see if anything needs to be replenished. This includes medicines; I always travel with paracetamol, just in case, except when I travel to the US, in which case I bring acetaminophen instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the packing list can’t keep track of everything. For example, if you try to list “make sure hotel is booked” or “tell wife that I’m travelling” on your list of what to pack, it turns out that you see that a little bit too late to be useful. Or that’s what my wife says, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have a “travel prep list” as well, which lists the things I need to do weeks in advance, or after I return. I have a document that keeps track of the lists for all of my upcoming trips: book flights, book hotel, register for conference, submit travel reimbursement, etc. This dramatically reduces the chance that I will book two hotel rooms for the same conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, there is &lt;a href=&quot;http://TripIt.com&quot;&gt;TripIt&lt;/a&gt;. TripIt is an amazing service that I have used for over a decade. Every time you get a confirmation email from an airline, hotel, travel agent, etc, you forward it to a special email address plans@tripit.com. TripIt parses all these emails and collects them into a single itinerary, using the dates to figure out which emails belong to the same trip. You never have to root around looking for a confirmation number again. It’s great! Especially clever: to sign up, just forward your first confirmation email to plans@tripit.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this leaves one more question. Why are professors always so forgetful in the first place? There’s a very good reason for that, actually. But that’s a different post…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="organizational advice" /><summary type="html">We had a fun time on the professors’ Facebook the other day, swapping stories of the dumbest travel mistakes that we’ve made. You know, booking flights to the wrong country, forgetting to book a hotel, registering for the conference twice, and other such hilarity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To PhD applicants: A word about department rankings</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/cs-rankings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To PhD applicants&amp;#58; A word about department rankings" /><published>2017-11-12T04:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-12T04:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/cs-rankings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/cs-rankings.html">&lt;p&gt;When I was applying for my PhD, I used rankings of computer science
departments to help me decide where to apply.
Rankings are never perfect, but I didn’t have access to
detailed knowledge of the research landscape,
and the rankings helped to steer me in the right direction.
In retrospect, I can see that the rankings were not perfect, and
I made one or two silly mistakes about where to apply,
but I would have made even more silly mistakes without them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m saying this to give you this context:
I’m not anti-ranking. Very possibly rankings have had a negative effect
on higher education overall, but they can be useful if done right, and if
you read them in the right way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Computing Research Association has just released a statement
&lt;a href=&quot;https://cra.org/cra-statement-us-news-world-report-rankings-computer-science-universities/&quot;&gt;urging everyone to ignore the new rankings&lt;/a&gt; of global computer science departments
from US News and World Report. I’m sorry to see this, because I found the US News rankings
helpful when I was an undergraduate. But I’ve read the new US News rankings, and I have to agree with the CRA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These US News rankings are absurd. They are garbage. No one should read them,
and I won’t even link to them. You can find them easily via a search engine. Please don’t. The ranking
methodology is flawed, for a simple reason that any computer science researcher
could tell them immediately. And we did. Influential researchers in computer science
pointed out the flaws directly to editors at US News; they were ignored.
I don’t know why the editors of US News would ignore this feedback,
unless they cared a lot about creating a controversy that would generate
page views, and not at all about helping students who are applying
for their PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll repeat: &lt;strong&gt;Please do not read these rankings at all, not even if you intend take my advice and ignore them.&lt;/strong&gt; If you click on them, even to laugh at them,
you are spending advertisers’ money to support this magazine in misleading
 PhD applicants
who are not as well informed as you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advice: If you need rankings, instead go to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://csrankings.org/&quot;&gt;CSRankings.org&lt;/a&gt;. This is a fully open ranking from &lt;a href=&quot;https://emeryberger.com/&quot;&gt;Prof Emery Berger&lt;/a&gt; at UMass Amherst that ranks global computer science departments
directly by the amount of research they produce. You can filter
the rankings by geographic area and research area. No ranking is perfect, but this is defensible and open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that rankings are only useful if you read them correctly.
Here are some thoughts about how to do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overall ranking is not the same as subject specific ranking.
The department ranked #50 isn’t ranked that way because its research is #50
in every area of CS. Instead, it will have some research areas that are #50 —
which is still pretty damn good — but a few groups that are in
the top five. If you are in one of those top groups, then you are in a top group, with all the same excitement and opportunity as the top groups
at a bigger name school.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disregard small differences in ranking. Ranking is an ill-defined
problem, so you can’t take small differences seriously. As far as overall strength goes,
the school ranked #1 is exactly the same as the school ranked #5.
Exactly the same. But #1 is going to be overall stronger than #18.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For your PhD, what matters most is your supervisor and their group,
rather than the department overall. This relates to what I said
above, and is probably worth a blog post of its own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rankings are not life. The distinctions that we are talking about
here are small distinctions at the very top. The school ranked #100
— I haven’t looked up what it is — is a fine university with brilliant
researchers where you will learn a lot. Here’s an analogy. The weakest football player in the English Premier League, who spends most of his time on
the bench, is still a prodigiously talented football
player who would run circles around anyone who you and I have ever met. The difference between Lionel Messi and that guy — that’s the level of difference we’re talking about here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point: &lt;strong&gt;Use rankings as a way to discover departments&lt;/strong&gt;
you didn’t know about that are strong in your area. Don’t use them
as a way to decide between departments: For that, you should be reading
the work of potential supervisors that interest you. Doing a PhD is about
learning to do research. What types of papers do you want to write?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="phd applications" /><summary type="html">When I was applying for my PhD, I used rankings of computer science
departments to help me decide where to apply.
Rankings are never perfect, but I didn’t have access to
detailed knowledge of the research landscape,
and the rankings helped to steer me in the right direction.
In retrospect, I can see that the rankings were not perfect, and
I made one or two silly mistakes about where to apply,
but I would have made even more silly mistakes without them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to read a research paper</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/read-a-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to read a research paper" /><published>2017-11-04T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-11-04T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/read-a-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/read-a-paper.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s lots of advice you can read about how to read a research paper. There’s some good advice in this paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S. Keshav. &lt;a href=&quot;http://ccr.sigcomm.org/online/files/p83-keshavA.pdf&quot;&gt;How to read a paper&lt;/a&gt;. ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review, 37(3):83–84, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s one tip that I can offer you to organise your reading of a paper that I can’t remember seeing elsewhere. Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the 5 minute summary that you would give to a Very Smart Friend?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t understand a paper until I can explain the paper to a smart person who hasn’t read it. I need to be able to explain enough to the VSF so that she understands: what problem the paper is trying to solve, what sort of methods does it use, and how does it relate to the literature, i.e., what does it add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s two rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule 1: You have to use your own words, summarising the paper without looking at it. If you find yourself repeating sentences from the paper, the you haven’t internalised the paper’s message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule 2: You cannot take &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; the paper says at face value. You can assume that the authors won’t lie to you. But they might oversell a bit, and if you are a independent expert, you might not agree with everything they claim, or with how they interpret the new evidence that they have provided. Or you might be able to describe what’s going on a little bit better than they managed. What do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think that they have shown?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of saying this: I know that my imaginary Very Smart Friend will jump on me if I say something inaccurate. So I don’t want to make a claim to my iVSF unless &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; can argue for it, based on what I have learned from the theory and experiments in the paper. If I just say something like “well, the authors claim X,” but X is controversial, or even dubious, then my iVSF will immediately want to know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they say that, do they really have evidence, and I had better have a answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be good to try this exercise even before you are done. After reading the introduction, how well can you guess what the methods will be, even before you read them? Then read to see if you were right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, I hope that I’ve convinced you that having an imaginary friend can help you in your research. You might not want to tell everyone on the internet that you have an imaginary friend, as I have just done, because it might not improve their respect for you.  But hey, if it’s good for your research, then where are your priorities?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="research advice" /><summary type="html">There’s lots of advice you can read about how to read a research paper. There’s some good advice in this paper:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My special-est email folder</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/10/special-email-folder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My special-est email folder" /><published>2017-10-07T10:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-10-07T10:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/10/special-email-folder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/10/special-email-folder.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a lot of different methods to organize my email. None of them work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of trying, I’ve come to the conclusion that the Gmail solution of “put all the email in one bucket and search” is the way to go. Over the years I have gotten very, very good at searching my email. But that’s a topic for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I wanted to mention a special email folder that I have. Maybe it’s the most important folder I have, even though I might only look at it once a year, if that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What could be so special? Emails to pick me up when I’m feeling down. You know which ones I mean. The emails that contained job offers, promotions, grant awards, or even just kind words from trusted senior colleagues. I archive emails like this, emails with special professional successes, in their own folder. Then every once in a while, if I’ve been dealing with a difficult situation or am having a particularly bad bout of impostor syndrome, I can open up the folder and look at it just for a minute, and then I feel a little bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask why these are &lt;em&gt;professional&lt;/em&gt; emails. Hopefully I’ve had happy things happen in my personal life as well? Don’t be too worried. It’s just that my personal life doesn’t usually happen over email. That’s what my wedding photos are for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got this idea from a blog post somewhere by some other professor, but I don’t remember who or where. If you do, please let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: Rob Zinkov has kindly reminded me that I learned about this idea
from the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/the-awesomest-7-year-postdoc-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-the-tenure-track-faculty-life/&quot;&gt;7 year postdoc&lt;/a&gt; blog post
by Radhika Nagpal about
life for new faculty members. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="email" /><summary type="html">I’ve tried a lot of different methods to organize my email. None of them work.</summary></entry></feed>
