<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-17T21:18:44-08:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Exclusive Or</title><subtitle>How to be creative, productive, and happy as a researcher. Advice and reflections from a working scientist in machine learning.</subtitle><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><entry><title type="html">Joy in Research</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2023/01/joy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Joy in Research" /><published>2023-01-01T11:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-01T11:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2023/01/joy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2023/01/joy.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to remember what machine learning conferences were like in person, but I think that I liked them a lot better when the field was smaller. It was easier to meet new people, to talk about new ideas in small groups of talented people who were really excited by them. The culture of the field has changed from back then, in intellectual ways that you know already, but the social ways are worth reflecting on, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Romanticizing the past is a sorry hobby for old men. I will not do that. All research communities have a callous system at their core — I’ve written about the &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/03/tournament-axe.html&quot;&gt;toxic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/04/worth.html&quot;&gt;forces&lt;/a&gt; that drive and derail research careers — that’s always been the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe now, these forces have gotten stronger and worse: The field is so much larger, we don’t all know each other, and the rewards for success are greater than I would have thought possible twenty years ago. The incentive to be competitive rather than kind, to fight on social media rather than to learn from people you disagree with, to speak hype rather than forthright truth, is so hard to resist. The temptation, in a word, to career rather than to learn. And as loath as I am to admit it, I have changed, too. Probably in similar ways, and for similar reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I wouldn’t want to go back. The most exciting time to be in this field is right now. But maybe I would go back in time, if just to grab something and come back. What I would bring with me is joy. Joy in reading a paper with a cute new idea, and chatting about it with friends over lunch. The joy that would impel us to make up a stupid song or a silly skit about our research workshop, with the same spirit of play to work out a new kind of algorithm, which may seem silly at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joy in learning, joy in sharing, and joy in trying things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy new year!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="new years" /><summary type="html">It’s hard to remember what machine learning conferences were like in person, but I think that I liked them a lot better when the field was smaller. It was easier to meet new people, to talk about new ideas in small groups of talented people who were really excited by them. The culture of the field has changed from back then, in intellectual ways that you know already, but the social ways are worth reflecting on, too. Romanticizing the past is a sorry hobby for old men. I will not do that. All research communities have a callous system at their core — I’ve written about the toxic forces that drive and derail research careers — that’s always been the case.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ICLR 2020: My first virtual conference</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2020/05/virtual-iclr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ICLR 2020: My first virtual conference" /><published>2020-05-10T12:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-10T12:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2020/05/virtual-iclr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2020/05/virtual-iclr.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(or: How I learned to stop worrying and love virtual conferencing.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many computer science conferences are becoming virtual this year,
due to travel restrictions.
I enjoy physical conferences, so I was a bit skeptical
about virtual conferences, despite their necessity.
Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://iclr.cc/virtual/index.html&quot;&gt;ICLR 2020&lt;/a&gt; was the first major machine learning
conference to be virtual,
this was a good chance to test my skepticism.
Here’s a personal report about the parts of the conference
that I had a chance to experience, how well they worked for me,
and what I would do differently the next time I attend
a virtual conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top, the bottom line:
ICLR was better than I expected a virtual conference could be.
Both the format and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iclR/iclr.github.io/&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; should be a model
for other computer science conferences that are going virtual.
Massive congratulations are in order for all of the organizers, 
including the chairs Sasha Rush, Shakir Mohamed,
Dawn Song, Kyunghyun Cho, and Martha White.
There’s still more work to be done to make virtual conferences great,
because we haven’t yet figured out serendipity, or
how to recreate
the fluid social dynamics of a large meeting.
But now we have a great starting point to experiment from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-it-who-was-there-what-happened&quot;&gt;What is it? Who was there? What happened?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The International Conference of Learning Representations (ICLR) is one
of the largest machine learning research conference.
The physical ICLR 2019 conference has 2700 attendees.
This year, the conference accepted 687 research papers from 2594 submissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organizers of ICLR put an incredible amount of effort
at short notice to build custom software to support the virtual conference
(their code is open source, see links at the end).
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@iclr_conf/format-for-the-iclr2020-virtual-conference-76716ddea640&quot;&gt;conference format&lt;/a&gt;
featured prerecorded talks, live Q&amp;amp;A sessions both for invited speakers,
and text chat rooms.
There were other parts of the conference where I didn’t spend much time:
I only spent a little time at the workshops, and I didn’t have a chance to
attend the virtual vendor booths or official conference socials. 
ICLR 2020 was big, even bigger than the in-person machine learning conferences:
over 5600 registrations, 1300+ speakers, one million page views, and 100k+ video watches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-loved-about-virtual-iclr&quot;&gt;What I loved about Virtual ICLR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suprisingly, &lt;strong&gt;I really loved the poster sessions.&lt;/strong&gt; Every accepted research
paper was presented as a virtual poster. Every paper had a web page
that collected together links to the paper, the reviews (this is ICLR — they use openreview),
a five-minute video by the authors, a text chat room, and links to a Zoom
videoconference room specifically for the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day of the conference had five 2-hour poster sessions, spread out to be convenient for
participants from different time zones. Of course, the videos were always available,
but each paper was assigned to two different poster session at which the authors could attend
the Zoom room and answer questions. Assigning each paper to two sessions was designed
to increase the number of time zones that were conventient for each poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five-minute videos were my favorite part of the conference.
They were synchronzied to slides, so if the talk was covering background you already knew,
or if you missed a point, you could click back and forth in the slides.
(In person, this is harder to do, and depends on the social and language skills of both participants.)
I found the videos were a great way to get an overview of many papers and decide
where I wanted to focus my time. They were much more polished and a little more in
depth than the elevator pitch that you get at a physical poster when you ask,
“Could you tell me a bit about this work?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Zoom rooms themselves were sparsely attended. I hopped into the rooms 
for probably a dozen papers, and usually I was the only one there, apart from the authors.
Perhaps twice there was one person already asking a question. 
For me, this was great, because then I could start a ncie conversation with the authors
(some tips on that later). 
The downside is I have learned a lot from hearing questions that my colleagues
have asked at posters — that didn’t happen here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text chat rooms for each paper were active. People would ask detailed technical
questions and the authors would respond. Some of the discussions were fairly in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way that virtual posters are arguably better than physical:
&lt;em&gt;you could not see who else was looking at the poster&lt;/em&gt;.
Indeed, even though the Zoom rooms were generally quiet, the posters got a fair amount of attention.
The median poster had 200 unique views, and the most popular had over 1000.
Machine learning is a trend-seeking community, for as long as I’ve been a part of it.
At physical conferences, posters from famous authors and research labs become very crowded,
so much so that they become short talks (a poster session of repeated loops,
like in Westworld) rather than scientific discussions. Hiding poster popularity prevented the bad aspects
of the rich-get-richer dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each poster session had its own page that listed the title and author
of each paper (but no institutions, again to prevent rich-get-richer) along with an automatically
generated thumbnail. These were randomly ordered for fairness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;invited talks worked well&lt;/strong&gt; also. These were prerecorded longer talks with
a live Q&amp;amp;A. If I remember right, the video of the talks were made available
the day before the Q&amp;amp;A. This worked well because what you get out of an invited talk,
you can get just as much from a recording, and the live Q&amp;amp;As were very active.
In some cases, speakers stayed for over an hour answering questions over
both audio and text chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;overall paper visualization&lt;/strong&gt; was well done. This plotted all of the papers as
points in 2D space, organized by topic. You could highlight papers by keyword, authoor,
and so on. These 2D visualizations are often a mess
(I even have &lt;a href=&quot;https://xuk.ai/darksight/&quot;&gt;a paper discussing that&lt;/a&gt;), but this one seemed to locate papers
together sensibly. I took some pride in that one of my papers was an outlier at the edge of the display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;virtual-vs-physical&quot;&gt;Virtual vs Physical?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, there are two points to coming to a conference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Networking. Meeting new people who I can learn from, and learning new things
from old colleagues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Broadening my view. I can attend a lot of posters and talks to get a broad snapshot
of subareas that I might not have time to follow in detail when arxiv preprints come out.
The curation function that a conference serves, as problematic as it is, really helps me here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These worked differently at a virtual conference. For broadening my view, the virtual
conference was actually better, because the five minute videos were overall nicer 
than the quick explanation that you might get at a physical poster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For networking, as you would expect, my experience was more mixed. 
On the good side, it was easier to meet the poster presenters, because others were Zoom-shy.
This was great for meeting PhD students. In a lot of ways, though,
&lt;strong&gt;I found networking harder at a virtual conference&lt;/strong&gt;. Here is what was harder to make happen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was hard to connect with old colleagues, because I didn’t know who was participating
in the virtual event when.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had fewer serendipitous meetings. I can’t count the number of research meetings
that have started impromptu at local coffeeshops near the conference.
Sometimes I will start talking to someone I don’t know well, only to find
that there is an unexpected connection
between our different research interests. This can result in collaborations,
invited talks, grant proposals…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Networking cascades. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theexclusive.org/2015/05/my-top-conference-attendance-tip.html&quot;&gt;When you meet one person, they might introduce you to others.&lt;/a&gt;
This can happen naturally, like when you are talking to someone and one of their colleagues
invites them to lunch. This is harder in a virtual format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advice-for-participants-how-to-virtual-conference-with-aplomb&quot;&gt;Advice for participants: How to virtual-conference with aplomb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending a virtual conference is a different skill from attending a physical one.
Here are some things that I will try to do better next time:
For participants:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As much as you can, clear your calendar. Treat the virtual conference as reserved time.
You say, “That’s hard for me.” I know. It was hard for me too. But if you can reserve
time to attend a physcial conference, you can do it for a virtual conference.
Really, no one will stop you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preparation helps. For physical conferences, I always have the best intentions to read lots
of papers on the plane, but it doesn’t always happen. For virtual conferences, I think that
preparation is more important because the face-to-face time (Zoom rooms etc) is even more limited.
I wish that I had watched more of the five minute videos in advance of the poster sessions.
I think it’s also good to be proactive about setting up individual meetings before the conference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How not to be shy during poster sessions. I have the impressions that many attendees
were reluctant to participate in the poster sessions because it felt a bit socially awkward,
and hard to have a good question.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have some &lt;strong&gt;advice for asking virtual poster questions&lt;/strong&gt; (this is an advice blog, after all).
First, embrace the awkwardness. Yeah, it is a bit awkward at first, but once you
start talking, it’s just another technical conversation like many you’ve had before.
Second, yeah, you do need a question, but it doesn’t need to be brilliant,
and you don’t need to have read the paper. “I watched the video, but I didn’t
understand how the Thagomizer works. Could you tell me a bit more about that?”
“Is your regularization scheme related to curriculum learning?”
“I’m really interested in your work, because my recent work is about machine learning
for baking sourdough. Do you think that your work could be applied to that?”
It’s that easy to start a conversation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-more-could-we-do-next-time&quot;&gt;What more could we do next time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take away two big positive lessons from virtual ICLR: poster sessions
can work virtually, and text chat helps a lot.
How can we do even better? How do we get more serendipity and networking
in a virtual conferences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support social networking, 
there is lots of room to &lt;strong&gt;experiment with using videoconferencing creatively&lt;/strong&gt;.
Perhaps we could see lists of who
is around the virtual conference at any one time (allowing people to explore anonymously if they prefer.)
Perhaps we can have low friction ways to create a one-off videoconferencing rooms,
which others can see and join. Maybe we could consider having “virtual receptions”:
a one-hour block of time where many people are present to have discussions,
and people can show up and self-organize videoconference discussions of even 3 or 4 people.
I sometimes joke that perhaps we could virtually replicate running into someone
in the hallway: 10% of the time, when you attempt to join the videoconference
room for a poster, you are redirected to a videoconference with a random participant instead.
That’s a bit silly, but random chat groups, perhaps in larger groups, and with safegards 
to prevent abuse, might feasible. Perhaps we will find creative ways to use social
media during a virtual conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great example of creative videoconferencing was ICLRTown: a 2D virtul world &lt;em&gt;cum&lt;/em&gt; videoconferencing system.
You moved a little 2D avatar around an 80s style graphic of a conference center.
When you get close enough to someone else’s sprite, you see their video
and can talk to them. We got chats of up to 9 people that way.
This was fun to play with, but it still seems a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I wonder to what extent the huge scale of ICLR actually &lt;em&gt;helped&lt;/em&gt; it to be a
virtual conference, making it easier to spread across timezones, or easier to get
a critical mass for live Q&amp;amp;A. Most computer sciences conferences are smaller
than ICLR, so different models might work well for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources-about-iclr-and-virtual-conferences&quot;&gt;Resources about ICLR and virtual conferences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this post wasn’t enough, here is more you can read if you find yourself
in the exciting but scary position of organizing a virtual conference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iclr.cc/virtual_2020/&quot;&gt;Public archive of all ICLR 2020 content&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@iclr_conf/format-for-the-iclr2020-virtual-conference-76716ddea640&quot;&gt;Blog post describing ICLR 2020 format&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@iclr_conf/gone-virtual-lessons-from-iclr2020-1743ce6164a3&quot;&gt;Blog post describing ICLR 2020 lessons learned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/srush_nlp/status/1253786329575538691&quot;&gt;Twitter thread describing ICLR software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/iclR/iclr.github.io/&quot;&gt;Source code for ICLR web site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.07668&quot;&gt;Report from EDBT/ICDT 2020 virtual conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acm.org/virtual-conferences&quot;&gt;ACM report of virutal conferences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="conferences" /><summary type="html">(or: How I learned to stop worrying and love virtual conferencing.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How do you break into a career in machine learning?</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2020/02/how-to-begin-in-machine-learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do you break into a career in machine learning?" /><published>2020-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2020/02/how-to-begin-in-machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2020/02/how-to-begin-in-machine-learning.html">&lt;p&gt;I got a question the other day about how to start a career in machine learning.
I gave the best answer that I could, but I’m not sure that my best was
very good. Can you help? If so, join the discussion on social media
(or send me a note privately):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I am currently studying for a master’s at [a good university outside
the United States &lt;em&gt;-cas&lt;/em&gt;] while working part-time as an NLP research engineer. I would like to ask you for some advice if that was possible.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My question is: without having outstanding grades or publications in top AI journals, how could I find my way towards a top Ph.D. program or at least research internship, is there any possibility? I am currently working on deep learning (paid job) and have some Ph.D. offers. Still, I feel that internships at companies like Google or Ph.D. positions at top research centers are impossible without previous experience in a similar place, which is like a snake biting its tail. Except for students with massive GPA scores, which is not my case.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I am happy with my current job, but so far, I have just been able to grasp the opportunities that I found, so I am thinking about trying to go abroad. Everything I have found is very applied, and I would like to study more abstract or generic (even exotic) topics, instead of applying existing neural architectures to specific domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots and lots of applicants to computer science PhD programs want to do machine learning, so admissions is very competitive. I don’t think it’s necessary to have publications to get into a PhD program, although it does help, and the higher you go in the rankings, the more that you need any help that you can get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure that I have better advice than to learn as much as you can, do good work, network with others, and work your way up the prestige ladder. 
It’s true that going to a very highly ranked school gives you an advantage, but I know very good researchers who did not have very good grades in undergrad, and even if you do your PhD at a lower ranked place, if your work is good, it still can stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, a question for my readers (all three of them),
what do you think?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="questions from readers" /><summary type="html">I got a question the other day about how to start a career in machine learning. I gave the best answer that I could, but I’m not sure that my best was very good. Can you help? If so, join the discussion on social media (or send me a note privately):</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The three PhD Comic strips that are actually good research advice</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2019/02/phd-comics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The three PhD Comic strips that are actually good research advice" /><published>2019-02-18T08:40:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-02-18T08:40:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2019/02/phd-comics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2019/02/phd-comics.html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this blog, then you already know about
&lt;a href=&quot;http://phdcomics.com&quot;&gt;PhD Comics&lt;/a&gt;. If you really haven’t
seen them before, click the link and read them now.
They are more insightful and funnier than anything
in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It goes without saying, however, that
you should not model your own career
on the characters in the PhD comics strip.
For one thing, they’ve been in grad school
for more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, though, there are three PhD comic strips,
and probably only three,
that are actually good research advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phdcomics.com/comics/archive.php?comicid=715&quot;&gt;Writing your thesis outline.&lt;/a&gt;
A thesis is daunting. How do you write an entire
book over five-plus years? Instead, I like to tell my students
to think and plan at the level of individual papers. Basically,
you have three content chapters of your thesis, and
so if you have three strong papers that fit together
thematically, then you set up one paper per each chapter,
and there you are! No sweat.
I call
this the “PhD Comics Guide to Writing Your Thesis.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phdcomics.com/comics/archive.php?comicid=1047&quot;&gt;Amount of time writing one email&lt;/a&gt;. I saw this comic
when I was a junior professor, and
I immediately realized: (a) this is so true,
and (b) I needed to act more like the professor
in the comic strip. This is how I learned
that when you have
many things to decide, you must decide quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://phdcomics.com/comics/archive.php?comicid=1436&quot;&gt;The evolution of intellectual freedom&lt;/a&gt;.
Sometimes you have
to take big risks in your work
and follow your own star. Once you learn
the basic technical skills needed for research, it is so easy
to do only incremental work, follow what the cool people are doing, and focus on what’s likely
to get you jobs and funding. There are good reasons to do
some of this, but if this is all that you do,
then why are you in research?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="advice in popular culture" /><category term="phd comics" /><summary type="html">If you’re reading this blog, then you already know about PhD Comics. If you really haven’t seen them before, click the link and read them now. They are more insightful and funnier than anything in this blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Know thyself. The New Year’s resolution that underlies all productivity advice</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2019/01/know-thyself.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Know thyself. The New Year's resolution that underlies all productivity advice" /><published>2019-01-05T08:40:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-01-05T08:40:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2019/01/know-thyself</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2019/01/know-thyself.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m a sucker for New Year’s resolutions.
Every year I make up a half dozen resolutions,
usually the same ones each year, and carefully track
my progress for at least two or three months
before I get busy and forget all about them.
And in all seriousness, I’m happy about this, because
sometimes, for maybe one resolution in four,
I’m still able to make a lasting
change in my habits. That’s more than enough
to justify the effort,
as long as I take the failures in good humor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be as silly about resolutions as I am,
or even to have any resolutions at all, but the underlying
principle is important for any creative work.
You could say that it’s the underlying principle
behind all of the advice in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to know yourself, understand the way you think,
adapt the way you work to the way you think,
and always keep looking for ways to work better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will have all kinds of little
preferences about when you are most alert, creative,
and productive. Maybe you like to work in the morning.
Maybe you like to have a bit of background noise,
like in a coffee shop. Maybe you need almost absolute
quiet. Maybe you like to work from home, or maybe
you prefer the structure of having an office,
where your work space is separate from home.
Maybe you like to pace around the office,
talking to yourself and gesticulating wildly.
Or maybe that’s just me. Ahem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is, you need to learn what makes
you think most effectively, and seek out that environment.
No one can do that for you. Your best work space
will be different
for you than it is for me. (And good thing, too, otherwise
  all of Google would be people bumping into each other
  in the hallways
  because they were too busy talking to themselves.)
The only way to know is to experiment and find out what
works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s also vital for us to keep experimenting,
no matter how senior we are in our careers.
One reason is (I think this is from David Allen),
“The better you get, the better you’d &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; get.”
As you become more accomplished, you gain a reputation
which means that more demands are placed on you.
Another reason is that no matter how good you are,
you haven’t learned all of the tricks.
Your mental rhythms change as you get older,
just as an athlete in his thirties trains differently
than a teenager. Finally, the creative challenges change
as you get later in your career, as you need to learn to
adapt to the way that the field has changed in twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s always appealed to me about the research
career is that you never stop learning.
This is as much true for how you set up
the environment of your work as it is for the
content of your work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="how to think" /><category term="creative productivity" /><summary type="html">I’m a sucker for New Year’s resolutions. Every year I make up a half dozen resolutions, usually the same ones each year, and carefully track my progress for at least two or three months before I get busy and forget all about them. And in all seriousness, I’m happy about this, because sometimes, for maybe one resolution in four, I’m still able to make a lasting change in my habits. That’s more than enough to justify the effort, as long as I take the failures in good humor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Present a Scientific Poster at a Mega-Conference</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/12/poster.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Present a Scientific Poster at a Mega-Conference" /><published>2018-12-30T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-12-30T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/12/poster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/12/poster.html">&lt;p&gt;A lot of scientific communication happens at
poster sessions. It’s a great way to learn
about the field, and to meet new people
with similar research interests. It’s also a great
way to be noticed in a crowded research field.
Presenting a poster is just as important,
and requires as much specialized skill,
as giving a 25-minute talk.
Way back when, before this blog became what it is, I wrote advice for &lt;a href=&quot;http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/csutton/advice/posters.html&quot;&gt;presenting research posters&lt;/a&gt;.
Back when I started attending research conferences,
advice like that was probably good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these days, I think we need a few more
tricks in our poster-presenting sleeves.
One of my favourite recent conferences,
NeurIPS, had over 9000 attendees this year.
Unavoidably, the room was a little bit loud, and
it wasn’t unusual for a poster to have
twenty people around it.
&lt;em&gt;When the conference gets this large,
you need to present your poster differently.&lt;/em&gt;
I saw posters where
one presenter carefully and quietly explained the poster
to one person, both of them intently facing the poster,
cheerfully oblivious to the fact that ten people were standing
behind them, patiently reading the poster.
If you are the presenter, don’t do this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, follow Sutton’s Three Rules for Presenting
a Popular Poster at a Mega-Conference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be aware of what’s going on around you.&lt;/strong&gt;
While you’re talking about your poster, people will
be both joining and leaving your audience.
You need to keep track of this.
First, this lets you acknowledge someone who joins,
by making eye contact and giving a quick smile or nod
as you speak. (I’m not too proud to admit that although
I try to do this for everyone, I’m even more likely to
do this when the new person is someone I know,
or someone famous.)
Second, having awareness lets you adapt your presentation,
because the way you talk to 2 or 3 people is different than
the way you talk to a crowd of 15 people. How so?
See the next two points.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use your body language.&lt;/strong&gt;
Congratulations! Your work has attracted a crowd,
and you have maintained the presence of mind to
notice. Now what?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Continue your short talk about the paper,
just like you had before. You just need to make clear that
you are talking to the whole group rather than one person.
You do that with your body language.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Face the entire group. Make yourself big.
Put your feet just a bit farther apart,
your shoulders up, your arms away from your body, and
your gestures large, so that everyone can see you.
Look around the entire group as you speak.
If you are doing this right, there will be a large semicircle around the poster, and you will be in a prominent
position at one side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You need to speak up.&lt;/strong&gt; If people can’t hear you,
they will move on to the next poster. You need to speak
loudly enough that you can be heard 15 feet away in a
loud room. My voice is naturally on the loud side,
but even I had to consciously exert my full effort
to project my voice
while I was presenting our NeurIPS poster.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;There are techniques for doing this without straining
your voice.
If your profession involves speaking, as is common
in academia, it might help to learn about this.
“The Right to Speak” by Patsy Rosenberg is one
book that has been recommended to me.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s that you say? It’s hard to do all of that
while talking about research at the same time?
Yes! It is. That’s why you need to practice your short presentation
until you know it well. This leaves you with mental
space that you can use to focus on your audience.
(Actually, this is good advice for all talks.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition from “small group poster talk”
to “large group poster talk” can be awkward, but you
manage it. You can say something to the earlier group like,
“I’m going to reset the presentation for these new people,
but feel free to jump in if you think of more questions.”
Stuff like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One time, I had just started presenting
the poster to one person when a group seemed to come
up out of nowhere. I just looked at my faithful
original audience and said, “You might want to take
a step back, because I’m about to shout.” I did, and he did. I didn’t restart my talk, but I added in a few background phrases here
and there to help the larger group get context.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="presentation advice" /><summary type="html">A lot of scientific communication happens at poster sessions. It’s a great way to learn about the field, and to meet new people with similar research interests. It’s also a great way to be noticed in a crowded research field. Presenting a poster is just as important, and requires as much specialized skill, as giving a 25-minute talk. Way back when, before this blog became what it is, I wrote advice for presenting research posters. Back when I started attending research conferences, advice like that was probably good enough.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part V&amp;amp;#58 If you really are an Impostor, then it’s not a Syndrome</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/09/impostor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part V&amp;#58 If you really are an Impostor, then it's not a Syndrome" /><published>2018-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-09-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/09/impostor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/09/impostor.html">&lt;figure class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
As you know, there isn’t really any solution to self-doubt. In the end,
you just have to write and doubt simultaneously.  
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&quot;quote-source&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;quote-author&quot;&gt;Zadie Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The final post of a series on
&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/stress%20in%20research&quot;&gt;stress in research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nice way to end this series would be to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;http://phdcomics.com/comics/archive.php?comicid=1973&quot;&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt;,
but I’m the wrong
person to write that blog, because I don’t think that I’ve ever literally
felt like an impostor. My self-doubt comes out in a different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll need to get a bit more personal, but an important warning first.
If you are currently serving on a committee that is considering whether to offer
me a new job, promotion, prize, or award, please can you stop reading now.
Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My self-doubt comes out like this.
I am secretly convinced that I am not good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already discussed how the
&lt;a href=&quot;/2018/03/tournament-axe.html&quot;&gt;Tournament of Research&lt;/a&gt;
is public. So I can see the accomplishments of those who have surpassed me
in the Tournament, and secretly doubt whether I am good enough to compete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see how quickly the field is moving, and how many new ideas
are being introduced every few weeks, and secretly doubt
whether I am good enough to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see the pressing  problems that our research
field is facing. I secretly doubt whether I am clever enough to create new ideas
that are subtle enough to solve these tricky problems.
I doubt whether I am good
enough to create the kind of work that I would like to create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;/tag/stress%20in%20research&quot;&gt;series of articles&lt;/a&gt; has had
three themes: one theoretical, one practical,
and one psychological. The theoretical insight is that
the research
community is structured in a way to grow and foster
your self-doubt, and it succeeds in almost all of us.
Self-doubt is, therefore, not your fault.
More practically, self-talk can be a good way to continue doing
good work in the face of self doubt. The psychological
theme has been on the role of ego in research:
necessary, but always carrying the dangers of jealousy
and doubt. Combining the final two themes,
the last advice I will give about
self-doubt is about using self-talk to manage your ego.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of advice suggests fighting self-doubt
with positive self-talk: “I really am good enough! I belong here!”  Try this and see if it helps you. Different
strategies will work for different people. For me,
positive self-talk does not seem to help; it is too hard
for me for disregard the objective evidence that
there really are people out there who are better than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead of reaffirming my ego, I use self-talk
to deny my ego. I push my thoughts away from myself,
and towards the tasks in front of me, which
are easy to get excited about, and then the fear goes away.
Imagine an actor, petrified with fear while
waiting to go on, who once onstage and forced to perform,
slips into the role without effort or doubt.
I try to feel like that when I sit down to my laptop.
Said another way: People report the fear that they &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;
an impostor. But it does not matter what you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;,
it matters what you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, in the end, none of the dark thoughts matter.
I am inadequate, I am not good enough, and it does not matter.
It does not matter because all the doubts, all the dark thoughts, are self centered claptrap,
exercises in destructive solipsism.  The doubts are all about me,
but when it comes to work, how I feel is unimportant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It does not matter how good I am.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I love the work
that I do, and people are willing to pay me to do it,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I continue to learn through my work,
to learn from my students, colleagues, and collaborators,
at the same time that they seem to be learning from me,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I can see new directions for my work,
to expand my knowledge and perhaps others’ as well,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as there is a chance, even a slim one, that I can create something
that will change the way people think, or in a small way, improve
the way the world works,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I can &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; all this, it does not matter how good I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt;.
As long as there remains much to do,
I am going to try to do it, whether I am good enough or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I reach the end of my career, and never do something that ever fully
matches my ambitions, my work will have accomplished
something, even if indirectly and in a small way.
I have had the privilege to participate in the worldwide, centuries-long conversation
of the community of scholars. And this larger conversation
has made a difference, I am sure, even if my own part has been small.
I have been part of the life of the research community, preserving, growing, and sharing
knowledge. That is
 enough to make my professional life worthwhile, even after all the papers that I’ve written have faded into obscurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s how I deal with self doubt.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><category term="popular" /><summary type="html">As you know, there isn’t really any solution to self-doubt. In the end, you just have to write and doubt simultaneously. Zadie Smith</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ill-Judged Britishness, and Self-Deprecation within a Power Dynamic</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/08/deprecation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ill-Judged Britishness, and Self-Deprecation within a Power Dynamic" /><published>2018-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/08/deprecation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/08/deprecation.html">&lt;p&gt;I really should know better. Twice now, I’ve done this to myself.
I was a social event with one of my PhD students,
like a party during a conference, where I was introducing
them to a colleague. Feeling relaxed after a beer
or two, I attempted an ill-judged joke, “So-and-so has
the misfortune of being one of my students.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often that type of humour works well for me,
and is enjoyed all around. Well, maybe I’m not perceptive
enough to tell if anyone else enjoys it, but I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misfortunate joke never works, though. Both times the student turned
and looked at me like I had three heads.
Why would I say something like that about myself? Why would
being my PhD student be a bad thing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second time this happened, I at least maintained
enough poise to explain myself. “Nothing to worry about,” I said quietly
to my student. “I’m just feeling a bit British.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Self-deprecation,” I said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, of course.” Immediate understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="attempts at social interaction" /><category term="anecdotes" /><category term="expat" /><summary type="html">I really should know better. Twice now, I’ve done this to myself. I was a social event with one of my PhD students, like a party during a conference, where I was introducing them to a colleague. Feeling relaxed after a beer or two, I attempted an ill-judged joke, “So-and-so has the misfortune of being one of my students.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part IV&amp;amp;#58 A Tsunami of Logistics</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/07/logistic-tsunami.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part IV&amp;#58 A Tsunami of Logistics" /><published>2018-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/07/logistic-tsunami</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/07/logistic-tsunami.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The fourth in a tidal wave of posts about
&lt;a href=&quot;/tag/stress%20in%20research&quot;&gt;stress in research&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a source of stress for people who have gotten a bit more senior
in their careers, like new professors or managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a previous post in the series, a colleague commented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What gets me is the daily tsunami of logistics: questions that need responses,
decisions that have to be made, scheduling, and millions of small deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every new professor mentions this. If senior professors complain about this
less often, perhaps it is because they are simply better at ignoring questions
that need responses. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making decisions is stressful for those who lack the training or personality.
A PhD trains you to think deeply and carefully about an issue.
Scientifically speaking, you want to reserve judgment when you don’t have all of
the information, not go ahead and make a snap decision anyway.
As an administrator, though, sometimes that is exactly what you must do.
Maybe the thing that stresses me the most, though, is when I inevitably fall
behind the tsunami, I hate the feeling that I’m letting people down.
This feeling is actually one of the things that bothers me most about
academia, even though I’m well aware that if I did spend all of my
time attending to logistics promptly, I would still be letting people down,
in a deeper way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics tsunami is, like all tsunamis, perilous. The obvious danger
is that you spend so much time sending emails
&lt;a href=&quot;http://theoatmeal.com/comics/email_monster&quot;&gt;like a tired diplomat&lt;/a&gt;
that you lose your time for work that requires deeper thought.
Your ability to do deep work is why you won your job in the first place,
so not doing it once you’ve reached a higher level is not so great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logistics tsunami brings another, more insidious danger.
This danger is not about losing
your time but losing your mind. Your unconscious mind, I mean.
A lot of our most important thinking happens unconsciously,
our brains churning in the background while our focus is elsewhere,
until the wonderful moment when a thought finally pops into our consciousness,
like Athena in the mind of Zeus.
For me, this usually happens when I’m walking.
For you, it might be in the shower, or when you are sitting with your coffee.
I really like the way that Female Science Professor talks about
&lt;a href=&quot;http://science-professor.blogspot.com/2014/11/this-is-your-brain-on-administration.html&quot;&gt;your brain on administration&lt;/a&gt;.
When you start doing too much administration, the tsunami starts to take
over your unconscious mind, and the wonderful ideas that pop up start to be
about what you can spend a tiny slice of your grant budget on, or
how to phrase that sensitive email, instead of what to write your
next paper about. This is the most terrible danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now delayed for too long the part of the blog where I explain my
optimistic but wise, surprising but helpful, advice on how
to manage the tsunami. I am afraid that I must report that
the delay didn’t help me come up with any better ideas.
All I can say is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When you have many decisions, you must decide quickly.&lt;/em&gt; This is the secret
that good decider-people know that you and I don’t. Me, I like to mull over
things. Then by the time I actually make a decision, I know I’m sure,
so I feel a lot better about it. That’s OK for big decisions, but not so good
for deciding whether you want to meet tomorrow at 1pm or 2pm.
When it doesn’t really matter, wrap up the matter quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learn how to partition your time.&lt;/em&gt; Deep thinking requires uninterrupted
blocks of time. These are hard to find, but you must.
I think that the optimal block size varies from person
to person. Some people split things up by day.
You could have “teaching days”, “admin days”, “research days”, and so on.
Some people enforce no-meeting days. Some people will work Sundays,
but only on research.
Some people don’t check email before 4PM.
Some people send lots of emails late at night because they’re tired anyway.
I don’t split things up by day, because I like to do small tasks
when I get tired from concentrating. I make sure to schedule meetings back
to back, to try to keep blocks of time for deeper work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Protect the time when you are most creative.&lt;/em&gt; When you go to partition
your time, you’ll want to remember what time of day you are most creative
and have the most energy. That is the time that you need to reserve for
the most creative work. If people often drop by your office — we all love
an open door policy — then this is the time to not &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; in your
office.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Make good use of odd chunks of time.&lt;/em&gt; As much as we bemoan smartphones,
they shine at this. If you only have 10 minutes until your next meeting,
the tsunami will happily offer you things that take only 10 minutes to do.
To be an effective professor, you need to play Tetris with time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need a to-do list.&lt;/em&gt; If you know about things you need to do
that aren’t written down, a part of your unconscious will repeat them over
and over, so you don’t forget. You have many more important jobs for
your unconscious mind than that. I like the principles behind the
&lt;a href=&quot;/2015/11/gtd-made-simple-why-i-think-internet.html&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done system&lt;/a&gt;
very much, although my practice is distinctly imperfect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Find a fast way to schedule meetings.&lt;/em&gt; Really a special case of the first
principle. If you spend 20 hours a week in meetings, it’s easy to spend
a couple hours a week arranging meetings. You need to make arranging a time
as simple as possible, using whatever tools work for you. For example,
I have my Google calendar hooked up to Doodle, so when an administrator
sends out a Doodle poll, I can respond in one click. Some online calendars
have features for creating appointment slots. Some people publish their
free/busy schedule publicly. Whatever works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Know when “good enough” is good enough.&lt;/em&gt; The easiest way to get more things
done is to spend less time doing each thing. Your research requires certain
habits of mind, careful and precise thought, perhaps. I guarantee you that
this level of clarity and precision is not required for your emails.
Jenny Pickerill has a nice
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JennyPickerill/status/985780112112091141&quot;&gt;Twitter thread on satisficing&lt;/a&gt;
as a professor.
Satisficing is more painful for tasks that are more central
to our mission. Any university class can be made 20% better at the cost
of twice as much prep time — don’t do it. (I received this advice,
second hand, from an award-winning lecturer!) I’m not saying that
you should be puzzling out your colleague’s slides for the first time
in front of the class, either. You need to find something in the middle,
and the same goes for the service that you do inside and outside
of the university.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><summary type="html">The fourth in a tidal wave of posts about stress in research.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Social Skills in Context, or How being a Professor is Kind of Like Being a Mafia Hitman</title><link href="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/06/mafia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Skills in Context, or How being a Professor is Kind of Like Being a Mafia Hitman" /><published>2018-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/06/mafia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.theexclusive.org/2018/06/mafia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Ruggiero&quot;&gt;Benjamin “Lefty Guns” Ruggiero&lt;/a&gt;
was a fearsome Mafia hitman in New York in the 70s.
According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_D._Pistone&quot;&gt;an undercover FBI agent&lt;/a&gt;
who knew him well, he was smart and savvy in underworld situations.
He could walk into a restaurant where he knew no one,
watch who talked to who, watch how they talked,
and work out who was in the underworld, who received more deference,
whether the restaurant was being extorted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other situations, a different story. The FBI agent,
Joseph Pistone, was himself an incredibly perceptive observer
(if he wasn’t, he’d have been murdered). He reports:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A lot of these wiseguys did not have the ability to move around the country.
Once you got these guys out of New York City, they were like fish out of water....
As they schooled me in the mafia, I had to school them on how to make airline reservations.
I am talking about a 49-year-old man,
telling him how to make airline reservations to three different cities, with an
open return, because we
did not know what date we were going to return to New York City.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption class=&quot;quote-source&quot;&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;quote-author&quot;&gt;Joseph Pistone&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;cite class=&quot;quote-title&quot;&gt;Donnie Brasco: My Undercover Life in the Mafia&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I was immediately reminded of computer science research.
In research situations, I think of myself as reasonably socially aware:
I have a network of mentors, students, and collaborators;
I can meet new colleagues and have interesting technical discussions;
I can even navigate the occasional difficult conversation when the need
arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But outside of work, I can be a bit more awkward,
or at least that’s what my wife says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stereotype technical people as having low social skills, and
I’ll admit knowing people who fully meet that stereotype.
The Mafia hitman reminds us that social skills are context specific:
you can be savvy in one type of situation, and clueless in another.
“Social skills” aren’t a single skill, any more than intellectual
skills are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the term implies something else. Social skills are skills.
You can learn them.
And it is in the interests of your career to do so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="social skills" /><category term="painfully extended metaphors" /><summary type="html">Benjamin “Lefty Guns” Ruggiero was a fearsome Mafia hitman in New York in the 70s. According to an undercover FBI agent who knew him well, he was smart and savvy in underworld situations. He could walk into a restaurant where he knew no one, watch who talked to who, watch how they talked, and work out who was in the underworld, who received more deference, whether the restaurant was being extorted.</summary></entry></feed>