<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://www.theexclusive.org//feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-03-03T18:28:35-05:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org///</id><title type="html">The Exclusive Or</title><subtitle>On academic, expatriate, and other unusual forms of life.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stress in Research. Part I: The Tournament and the Axe</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/03/tournament-axe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stress in Research. Part I&amp;#58; The Tournament and the Axe" /><published>2018-03-03T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/03/tournament-axe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2018/03/tournament-axe.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Perhaps the first post in a series.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From one point of view, research is the best job in the world. You get to be creative and follow your curiosity. You are always learning; if you ever stop, you have stopped doing research. You can collaborate with brilliant people, and help young smart people to find the frontiers of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for all that, I think research will never stop causing me heartache and stress. If you have any capacity in your psyche for self-doubt, you will find that capacity nurtured and magnified during your career in research. But why should this be? The requirements of the job are blessedly open-ended, and we are granted substantial flexibility in how we manage our work. I mean, come on, how stressful can a job be if you’re not expected to roll in to work until 10 o’clock in the morning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this series, I will try to isolate and understand the sources of stress and in research, and how we might cope. I say “isolate”, “cope”, and not “eliminate” — I suspect that top-quality work is not possible without accepting some stress. But maybe there’s a way to get by accepting a little bit less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first triggers of stress that I want to talk about arise as a consequence of how people get jobs in research, and how the research community is structured. These are the Tournament and the Axe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the Tournament. The research community is structured around an series of increasingly more selective, and more difficult, international tournaments. Most undergraduate students choose to focus their work elsewhere, but of those that choose to do a PhD, most — including your humble author — are not admitted to their first-choice school. Of those who start a PhD,
many do not complete it. Of those who complete their PhD, many do not go on to another research position.
Of those who become assistant professors in the US, some do not receive tenure.
Finally, even of the top researchers, those who have a large group and regularly
publish well-received papers, only a small number of them can honestly say that
they have ever in their career achieved a groundbreaking new result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now let’s consider your competition in the Tournament, your international colleagues in the research community. When you first join a research community, usually by attending your first workshop or conference, it’s overwhelming to meet so many new interesting people, who are fascinated by the same arcane technology as you, &lt;em&gt;and who all seem smarter than you&lt;/em&gt;. This is partly an illusion: all these people have been around the community longer than you, so they simply have more background and experience, not more raw power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s truth in the illusion too: &lt;em&gt;There really are lots of people smarter than you&lt;/em&gt;. That is no insult. I’ll explain. For the sake of argument, let’s suppose that you are a unique genius, a special talent, one in a million. Even if you are one in a million, that means there are
7600 people in the world who are smarter than you. And the organizations of the research community are
 specifically designed to help you to meet them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, the outcome of the Tournament is public. The papers we publish, the prestigious jobs that we accept, the awards that we win, these are all public. The people stronger than you, or luckier, you can see the evidence of their success. And you suspect that others, your colleagues and friends, can see where you stand as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, the Axe. Many levels of the Tournament are up or out. You either succeed in a competition to move the next level, or you move to a career outside of research. The tenure system for assistant professors in the United States is famously up or out, but all earlier levels of your career path are, too. For example, I thought being a postdoctoral researcher was the best job in the world. I loved coming in to work every day. But I also knew there was the Axe over my head. If I hadn’t made enough progress in the two years that I had, I might not be able to remain in a research active position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this together causes a lot of stress, or at least it has for me. I like to think that there are attitudes and habits of mind that can reduce the stress of the Tournament, at least a little bit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understand that every Tournament is also a game. Success in the Tournament is not solely a reflection of your intelligence or your skill, but also your ability to play. It’s so easy to conflate your success in your career with your self-worth, but to do so too strongly is destructive. Disconnect your self-worth and your regard for others from performance in the Tournament.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Appreciate that winning the Tournament is not always the right move. The trap of the Tournament is that because it is a game, we naturally feel that winning a game is better than losing it. Not so. Choosing to leave a game is better than winning, when the game is not worth playing — when you enjoy other careers more than research, or if another career provides a better path for you to contribute professionally to the world. It would be almost a cliche to say “there is no shame” in leaving research, but it would also be a grave disservice, the language already buying into the bogus narrative that the competitions are there to be won. So I say instead: To start down one career path, recognize that it is not the best way for you to contribute, and choose another — I salute
and admire the strength and self-knowledge that is needed to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Tournament is not the core of research. I’ve been describing the research community as a competitive, perhaps even unfriendly, place. And it is competitive. But I’ve not found it to be unfriendly. I’ve met so many colleagues who have helped me by collaborating with me, explaining their work, graciously helping me to understand the field better. This creates the cognitive dissonance, how can the community be both competitive and helpful at the same time? I reconcile these views by &lt;em&gt;viewing competition as a type of collaboration&lt;/em&gt;. We have, together, decided to build a competition for attention, in the hope that it will help all of us to reach our full potential and teach each other as much as we can. So it is not the competition that is central to research, but  learning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To paraphrase the philosopher &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0110912/quotes/qt0447139&quot;&gt;Marsellus Wallace&lt;/a&gt;, jealously only hurts. It never helps. You meet someone smarter than you, someone who has accomplished more than you
despite being ten years younger, it’s all right to be impressed or amazed, but not jealous.
You need to train yourself to think instead: hey, what a great person to learn from!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Accept the existence of the Axe. Perhaps not helpful advice, because it is too easily said, but still important. There is nothing to be gained by spending too much time staring at the Axe above you. You know it’s there and you know it’s sharp. You still need to get on with what you have to do, if you intend to stay in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="stress in research" /><summary type="html">Perhaps the first post in a series.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Travel a lot? Here’s how to stay organized, like professors do</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/12/travel-professor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Travel a lot? Here's how to stay organized, like professors do" /><published>2017-12-02T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-02T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/12/travel-professor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/12/travel-professor.html">&lt;p&gt;We had a fun time on the professors’ Facebook the other day, swapping stories of the dumbest travel mistakes that we’ve made. You know, booking flights to the wrong country, forgetting to book a hotel, registering for the conference twice, and other such hilarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s face it, professors travel a lot. We are also very bad at remembering things. This is a combination that makes for comedy, unless you’re the poor sod who has to live through it. (That’s &lt;em&gt;Professor&lt;/em&gt; Sod, to you.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is, from long and painful experience, I’ve learned how to not to forget things as often when I travel. And now I will tell you my secrets, if I can remember them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep a &lt;em&gt;packing list&lt;/em&gt; (shocker!) that I reuse every time I pack my bags. I have a master list that I keep electronically and make a copy of for each trip. The important part is: Every time I arrive somewhere and forget something (toothpaste, underwear, etc), I add it to the master packing list for next time. After many years of this, I am now convinced that this list now contains everything I could possibly want to bring, and now I will never forget to pack something ever again. Well, hardly ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For toiletries I have an additional system, as they are too easy to forget. I keep a separate complete set of toiletries in a drawer, for travelling only. When I pack, I just unload the drawer into my luggage, and I know I have everything. When I return, I return the toiletries to the drawer, checking to see if anything needs to be replenished. This includes medicines; I always travel with paracetamol, just in case, except when I travel to the US, in which case I bring acetaminophen instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the packing list can’t keep track of everything. For example, if you try to list “make sure hotel is booked” or “tell wife that I’m travelling” on your list of what to pack, it turns out that you see that a little bit too late to be useful. Or that’s what my wife says, anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have a “travel prep list” as well, which lists the things I need to do weeks in advance, or after I return. I have a document that keeps track of the lists for all of my upcoming trips: book flights, book hotel, register for conference, submit travel reimbursement, etc. This dramatically reduces the chance that I will book two hotel rooms for the same conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, there is &lt;a href=&quot;http://TripIt.com&quot;&gt;TripIt&lt;/a&gt;. TripIt is an amazing service that I have used for over a decade. Every time you get a confirmation email from an airline, hotel, travel agent, etc, you forward it to a special email address plans@tripit.com. TripIt parses all these emails and collects them into a single itinerary, using the dates to figure out which emails belong to the same trip. You never have to root around looking for a confirmation number again. It’s great! Especially clever: to sign up, just forward your first confirmation email to plans@tripit.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this leaves one more question. Why are professors always so forgetful in the first place? There’s a very good reason for that, actually. But that’s a different post…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="organizational advice" /><summary type="html">We had a fun time on the professors’ Facebook the other day, swapping stories of the dumbest travel mistakes that we’ve made. You know, booking flights to the wrong country, forgetting to book a hotel, registering for the conference twice, and other such hilarity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">To PhD applicants: A word about department rankings</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/cs-rankings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To PhD applicants&amp;#58; A word about department rankings" /><published>2017-11-12T07:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-12T07:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/cs-rankings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/cs-rankings.html">&lt;p&gt;When I was applying for my PhD, I used rankings of computer science
departments to help me decide where to apply.
Rankings are never perfect, but I didn’t have access to
detailed knowledge of the research landscape,
and the rankings helped to steer me in the right direction.
In retrospect, I can see that the rankings were not perfect, and
I made one or two silly mistakes about where to apply,
but I would have made even more silly mistakes without them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m saying this to give you this context:
I’m not anti-ranking. Very possibly rankings have had a negative effect
on higher education overall, but they can be useful if done right, and if
you read them in the right way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Computing Research Association has just released a statement
&lt;a href=&quot;https://cra.org/cra-statement-us-news-world-report-rankings-computer-science-universities/&quot;&gt;urging everyone to ignore the new rankings&lt;/a&gt; of global computer science departments
from US News and World Report. I’m sorry to see this, because I found the US News rankings
helpful when I was an undergraduate. But I’ve read the new US News rankings, and I have to agree with the CRA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These US News rankings are absurd. They are garbage. No one should read them,
and I won’t even link to them. You can find them easily via a search engine. Please don’t. The ranking
methodology is flawed, for a simple reason that any computer science researcher
could tell them immediately. And we did. Influential researchers in computer science
pointed out the flaws directly to editors at US News; they were ignored.
I don’t know why the editors of US News would ignore this feedback,
unless they cared a lot about creating a controversy that would generate
page views, and not at all about helping students who are applying
for their PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll repeat: &lt;strong&gt;Please do not read these rankings at all, not even if you intend take my advice and ignore them.&lt;/strong&gt; If you click on them, even to laugh at them,
you are spending advertisers’ money to support this magazine in misleading
 PhD applicants
who are not as well informed as you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advice: If you need rankings, instead go to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://csrankings.org/&quot;&gt;CSRankings.org&lt;/a&gt;. This is a fully open ranking from &lt;a href=&quot;https://emeryberger.com/&quot;&gt;Prof Emery Berger&lt;/a&gt; at UMass Amherst that ranks global computer science departments
directly by the amount of research they produce. You can filter
the rankings by geographic area and research area. No ranking is perfect, but this is defensible and open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned that rankings are only useful if you read them correctly.
Here are some thoughts about how to do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overall ranking is not the same as subject specific ranking.
The department ranked #50 isn’t ranked that way because its research is #50
in every area of CS. Instead, it will have some research areas that are #50 —
which is still pretty damn good — but a few groups that are in
the top five. If you are in one of those top groups, then you are in a top group, with all the same excitement and opportunity as the top groups
at a bigger name school.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disregard small differences in ranking. Ranking is an ill-defined
problem, so you can’t take small differences seriously. As far as overall strength goes,
the school ranked #1 is exactly the same as the school ranked #5.
Exactly the same. But #1 is going to be overall stronger than #18.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For your PhD, what matters most is your supervisor and their group,
rather than the department overall. This relates to what I said
above, and is probably worth a blog post of its own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rankings are not life. The distinctions that we are talking about
here are small distinctions at the very top. The school ranked #100
— I haven’t looked up what it is — is a fine university with brilliant
researchers where you will learn a lot. Here’s an analogy. The weakest football player in the English Premier League, who spends most of his time on
the bench, is still a prodigiously talented football
player who would run circles around anyone who you and I have ever met. The difference between Lionel Messi and that guy — that’s the level of difference we’re talking about here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point: &lt;strong&gt;Use rankings as a way to discover departments&lt;/strong&gt;
you didn’t know about that are strong in your area. Don’t use them
as a way to decide between departments: For that, you should be reading
the work of potential supervisors that interest you. Doing a PhD is about
learning to do research. What types of papers do you want to write?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="phd applications" /><summary type="html">When I was applying for my PhD, I used rankings of computer science
departments to help me decide where to apply.
Rankings are never perfect, but I didn’t have access to
detailed knowledge of the research landscape,
and the rankings helped to steer me in the right direction.
In retrospect, I can see that the rankings were not perfect, and
I made one or two silly mistakes about where to apply,
but I would have made even more silly mistakes without them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to read a research paper</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/read-a-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to read a research paper" /><published>2017-11-04T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-11-04T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/read-a-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/11/read-a-paper.html">&lt;p&gt;There’s lots of advice you can read about how to read a research paper. There’s some good advice in this paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S. Keshav. &lt;a href=&quot;http://ccr.sigcomm.org/online/files/p83-keshavA.pdf&quot;&gt;How to read a paper&lt;/a&gt;. ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review, 37(3):83–84, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s one tip that I can offer you to organise your reading of a paper that I can’t remember seeing elsewhere. Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the 5 minute summary that you would give to a Very Smart Friend?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t understand a paper until I can explain the paper to a smart person who hasn’t read it. I need to be able to explain enough to the VSF so that she understands: what problem the paper is trying to solve, what sort of methods does it use, and how does it relate to the literature, i.e., what does it add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s two rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule 1: You have to use your own words, summarising the paper without looking at it. If you find yourself repeating sentences from the paper, the you haven’t internalised the paper’s message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule 2: You cannot take &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; the paper says at face value. You can assume that the authors won’t lie to you. But they might oversell a bit, and if you are a independent expert, you might not agree with everything they claim, or with how they interpret the new evidence that they have provided. Or you might be able to describe what’s going on a little bit better than they managed. What do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; think that they have shown?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of saying this: I know that my imaginary Very Smart Friend will jump on me if I say something inaccurate. So I don’t want to make a claim to my iVSF unless &lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; can argue for it, based on what I have learned from the theory and experiments in the paper. If I just say something like “well, the authors claim X,” but X is controversial, or even dubious, then my iVSF will immediately want to know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they say that, do they really have evidence, and I had better have a answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also be good to try this exercise even before you are done. After reading the introduction, how well can you guess what the methods will be, even before you read them? Then read to see if you were right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum up, I hope that I’ve convinced you that having an imaginary friend can help you in your research. You might not want to tell everyone on the internet that you have an imaginary friend, as I have just done, because it might not improve their respect for you.  But hey, if it’s good for your research, then where are your priorities?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="research advice" /><summary type="html">There’s lots of advice you can read about how to read a research paper. There’s some good advice in this paper:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My special-est email folder</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/10/special-email-folder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My special-est email folder" /><published>2017-10-07T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-07T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/10/special-email-folder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/10/special-email-folder.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried a lot of different methods to organize my email. None of them work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of trying, I’ve come to the conclusion that the Gmail solution of “put all the email in one bucket and search” is the way to go. Over the years I have gotten very, very good at searching my email. But that’s a topic for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I wanted to mention a special email folder that I have. Maybe it’s the most important folder I have, even though I might only look at it once a year, if that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What could be so special? Emails to pick me up when I’m feeling down. You know which ones I mean. The emails that contained job offers, promotions, grant awards, or even just kind words from trusted senior colleagues. I archive emails like this, emails with special professional successes, in their own folder. Then every once in a while, if I’ve been dealing with a difficult situation or am having a particularly bad bout of impostor syndrome, I can open up the folder and look at it just for a minute, and then I feel a little bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might ask why these are &lt;em&gt;professional&lt;/em&gt; emails. Hopefully I’ve had happy things happen in my personal life as well? Don’t be too worried. It’s just that my personal life doesn’t usually happen over email. That’s what my wedding photos are for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got this idea from a blog post somewhere by some other professor, but I don’t remember who or where. If you do, please let me know in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: Rob Zinkov has kindly reminded me that I learned about this idea
from the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/the-awesomest-7-year-postdoc-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-the-tenure-track-faculty-life/&quot;&gt;7 year postdoc&lt;/a&gt; blog post
by Radhika Nagpal about
life for new faculty members. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="email" /><summary type="html">I’ve tried a lot of different methods to organize my email. None of them work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does the world need one more blog about arxiv and double blind review?</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/09/arxiv-double-blind.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does the world need one more blog about arxiv and double blind review?" /><published>2017-09-19T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-19T08:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/09/arxiv-double-blind</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/09/arxiv-double-blind.html">&lt;p&gt;There has been a &lt;a href=&quot;https://gridworld.wordpress.com/2015/07/20/arxiv-heaven-or-hell/&quot;&gt;lively&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://chairs-blog.acl2017.org/2017/03/02/arxiv-and-double-blind-reviewing-revisited/&quot;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://chairs-blog.acl2017.org/2017/02/19/arxiv-and-the-future-of-double-blind-conference-reviewing/&quot;&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt; about the review process for research paper submissions, and how to deal with the fact that double-blind review becomes more difficult when many papers are prepublished on sites like arxiv.org before submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to start from two assumptions:
&lt;em&gt;double blind reviewing is good&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;prepublication is good.&lt;/em&gt; 
You can disagree with either assumption, or you could think that double-blind
is so much more important than than prepublication that it should
be preserved at all costs, or vice versa. People hold all of those views,
and it would take an even longer post to pull all that apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I’d to think about how to reconcile these two assumptions, because I do believe them both, and how to obtain an engineering trade-off that aims at most of the advantages of both, most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have said that allowing papers to be prepublished anonymously would be a good compromise. An appealing idea, but
I worry that it may be
a bad one. Instead, I’ll argue that a good compromise is this:  Accept that papers will be de-blinded, but design the double-blind review process to compensate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the underlying point is that the conflict isn’t black and white. For double blind to work, it’s not necessary for 100% of the submissions to be unblind&lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt;, i.e., have their author identities be undiscoverable online. I might even suggest that it’s possible to have effective double blind when &lt;em&gt;all author identities&lt;/em&gt; are available online. Just because a paper is unblind&lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt; does not mean that the reviewers are unblind&lt;em&gt;ed&lt;/em&gt; — perhaps they have not seen it, or perhaps they saw it in an email with 100 other papers and don’t remember having seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-shouldnt-we-do&quot;&gt;What shouldn’t we do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some recommendations that I’ve seen that unfortunately I don’t think will work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anti-recommendation-1-i-know-lets-have-an-anonymous-version-of-arxiv&quot;&gt;Anti-Recommendation 1: I know. Let’s have an anonymous version of arxiv.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of people have suggested allowing authors to prepublish papers
anonymously (incidentally, there are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mhhe.com/math/calc/smithminton2e/cd/tools/timeline/bernoulli_1.html&quot;&gt;amusing precendents for this&lt;/a&gt; in the history of mathematics). This could be implemented via an overlay of arxiv, or a new feature added to arxiv itself, that would allow authors to temporary hide their identity. Let’s call this AnonArxiv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submissions to AnonArxiv would be immediately available to all but without the author names. Then, once the paper is accepted, AnonArxiv would reveal the author names, while preserving the time stamp of the anonymous submission. The conference would then require that if submissions are prepublished, they must be prepublished anonymously; any other prepublished submissions will be rejected without review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think this was a cool idea. Now I don’t. It neglects a 
fundamental principle that we are sadly all familiar with,
that &lt;em&gt;most papers are rejected&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say I post a great paper to AnonArxiv and submit it to ACL. Like most papers it is rejected. I’m convinced that the reviewers have made a mistake, and so I want to resubmit it to EMNLP. How do we handle this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could (1) require resubmissions to remain anonymous. After rejection, I must choose whether to unblind the submission on AnonArxiv, in which case it cannot be resubmitted to other conferences, or whether to keep the submission anonymous, in which case the paper could spend a year-plus as anonymous, until it is finally accepted. This seems an unreasonable choice to force onto authors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or we could (2) allow authors, after one rejection, to unblind their AnonArxiv submissions and resubmit to a future conference. This has the benefit that papers only spend a few months as public-but-anonymous, which is not so bad.
But I’m not sure it works. For one, this is difficult to enforce, because apart from the honor system, the information about whether a paper was previously submitted is confidential (keep in mind that the original submission might have been outside the NLP community). But more fundamentally, what would we do for first-time submissions that violate this rule, reject them without review? How would we justify doing that when there are many second-time submissions whose authors are already public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would also mean that if I submit a paper to a conference outside of NLP which allows prepublication and get rejected, I would not be able subsequently decide that an NLP conference would be a better fit, and resubmit there. It might be possible to implement a special dispensation in this case, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With some regret, I come to the conclusion that AnonArxiv won’t work. That said, AnonArxiv variant (2) might work if a large enough percentage of submissions were first time submits. Then we’d have the majority of the papers on AnonArxiv, and hence unblindable, which might be good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;perhaps-anti-recommendation-require-prepublication-to-be-declared&quot;&gt;Perhaps Anti-Recommendation: Require prepublication to be declared&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACL 2017 required all submissions to &lt;a href=&quot;http://acl2017.org/calls/papers/#multiple-submission-policy&quot;&gt;declare if they had been prepublished&lt;/a&gt;. Reviewers were notified that a paper had been prepublished. Prepublished papers that were not declared as such were summarily rejected. Unfortunately I don’t understand the rationale for how this stringent requirement was meant to help. Remember, the goal is not to prevent all papers from being unblind-&lt;em&gt;able&lt;/em&gt;, it’s to prevent too many papers from being unblind-&lt;em&gt;ed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could be a good idea if the hope is to warn reviewers that they should be careful about searching the web for the paper’s title during the review process. The problem with this idea though, is that it does not help if the authors very reasonable prepublish the paper just &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; submission. So really, all reviewers need to be careful, all the time, and the extra heads up maybe isn’t too helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the idea was to simply to gain more information about how many papers are prepublished, then I totally agree with asking the question, but I do not see why penalties for non-compliance were necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the idea was to handle prepublished papers differently in the review process than non-prepublished ones, then I am not sure why this is necessary. Instead, I’ll advocate below that we handle the review process of &lt;em&gt;unblinded&lt;/em&gt; papers differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would argue that it might make sense for conferences to request that authors declare prepublication, but that no penalties for noncompliance be used in future years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-but-thats-actually-an-orthogonal-issue-lets-use-openreviewnet&quot;&gt;Recommendation-But-That’s-Actually-An-Orthogonal-Issue: Let’s use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openreview.net&quot;&gt;OpenReview.Net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also read the suggestion that the NLP community switch to running conferences on OpenReview. I love OpenReview, and I eagerly await the day when I can go onto a site like OpenReview and pull up any paper in computer science, from any venue, from any year past or present, and find a lively and informative discussion online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But OpenReview is a software platform, not a reviewing process. It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://openreview.net/pdf?id=xf0zSBd2iufMg&quot;&gt;specifically designed&lt;/a&gt; to allow conference chairs to configure what information about the reviews and authors should be made public and when. It’s not designed to answer the policy questions about whether submissions should be anonymous and what happens after they are rejected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;all-right-wise-guy-so-&quot;&gt;All right, wise guy, so …?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to square the circle is to try adapting reviewing norms to adjust and compensate for the fact that it is more likely for papers to be unblinded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conferences are already doing these things, so I don’t claim to have any new ideas. But I think it’s useful to bring together the arguments for these ideas, rather than having programme chairs have to reconstruct these arguments for themselves every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-1-clarify-norms-for-reviewers&quot;&gt;Recommendation 1: Clarify Norms for Reviewers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the author information for all submissions are public online, then reviewers, area chairs, and programme chairs can take steps to reduce the chances that a submission is unblinded, and to minimize the consequences when one is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reviewers&lt;/strong&gt; should avoid making Web searches that would be likely to reveal the authors of the paper. It can often happen that a well-meaning search for related work inadvertently turns up an unblinded copy of the paper. I am not saying that reviewers should never search for related work, but it carries risks — it always has (ten years ago I had a reviewer of one of my papers deblinded by a tech report) — and reviewers should try to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the reviewer feels that a Web search is necessary, they should hold off until they have read the paper completely and formed an initial impression of it. This allows reviewers to apply the bias of cognitive dissonance to counteract the potential bias of unblinding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If reviewers learn the author identities, then they must let the relevant person — who could variously go by the title “programme chair”, “programme committee member”, “meta-reviewer”, “senior PC member”, “area chair”, etc; I’ll use the term “area chair” (AC) — know this right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Area chairs&lt;/strong&gt; should be prepared to apply their judgment to weigh the reviewers’ comments differently when some reviewers are unblinded. Consider a paper like this: it has two negative reviews and one positive review, but the positive reviewer has been unblinded, the paper comes from a famous group so there is possibility of unconscious bias, and the AC believes that the negative comments have merit. Then the AC should be prepared to give less weight to the positive reviewer. In other examples, perhaps all three reviews are positive, or the authors are lesser-known, and so unlikely to engender positive bias. Then downweighting unblinded reviewers may not be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programme chairs&lt;/strong&gt; should carefully write their instructions to reviewers and area chairs to make these expectations clear. They should also be prepared to assist ACs with borderline cases where there is possibility of bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t know if these steps alone will reduce the percentage of unblind-&lt;em&gt;ed&lt;/em&gt; submissions to an acceptable level. For example, if the percentage of unblinded reviews reaches, say, 80%, this recommendation becomes more like a band-aid that would be unlikely to preserve the benefits of double-blind review. Which brings us to the next point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;recommendation-2-measure-and-monitor&quot;&gt;Recommendation 2: Measure and Monitor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the heat around this discussion may be because we are, as it were, debating in the blind. It is not difficult to gather more evidence than we have now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should be able to measure and publicize the percentage of submissions and accepted papers which are prepublished.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although a bit more delicate, we should be able to estimate the percentage of submissions which are not first time submits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we follow recommendation 1, we should also be able to monitor the percentage of reviews which are unblinded and the percentage of submissions which have had 1, 2, or 3 unblinded reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should also attempt to record measures of diversity in the accepted papers in terms of authors and institutions. We should keep tracking those measures, monitor for decreases, and the presumed negative correlation with percentage of unblindedness.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="publication models" /><summary type="html">There has been a lively debate recently about the review process for research paper submissions, and how to deal with the fact that double-blind review becomes more difficult when many papers are prepublished on sites like arxiv.org before submission.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The not-so-great checked vs carry on debate</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/09/pack-bags.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The not-so-great checked vs carry on debate" /><published>2017-09-02T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-02T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/09/pack-bags</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/09/pack-bags.html">&lt;p&gt;This time, some advice of a lighter sort. How light? Depends how well you pack!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hear a lot of frequent air travelers say that you should never check bags if you can avoid it, but I think it’s not always clear cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do usually travel with only a carry on. This has a lot of advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t need to queue at the ticket counter to drop off bags. If you’ve checked in online, using your phone is easiest but printing your boarding pass is still good, then you can go straight to security and the gate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t need to wait at baggage claim on arrival. This is an especially big win if you are arriving late at night.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s easier to switch flights at the last minute. You might wonder why you’d want to do this if you’ve planned ahead. You’ll stop wondering when your first flight arrives early and you wish you could jump on an earlier connecting flight. Or when your first flight is delayed but you still have a chance to catch a different connecting flight. I’m still annoyed at the time United Airlines prevented me from doing this by checking my bag at the gate unnecessarily.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, for some trips it can be more convenient to check your bags, even if you could squeeze into a smaller bag. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can bring a bigger bag that holds more. (duh)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You don’t need to lug the bag around the airport. This removes stress during a long connection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can fill up your checked bag with liquids and gels. This is especially useful if you’d like to bring gifts of food and drink back to your friends, family, or perhaps to a select group of academic bloggers who you particularly admire.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are running a few minutes late to the gate, the plane is more likely to wait for you, because if they don’t, they need to find and remove your bag from the hold.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For direct flights I think it’s clear that carry on wins most of the time, but if you have a connection then it may well depend on your itinerary.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="travel tips" /><summary type="html">This time, some advice of a lighter sort. How light? Depends how well you pack!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A first lecture on time management</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/08/time-management.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A first lecture on time management" /><published>2017-08-05T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-05T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/08/time-management</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/08/time-management.html">&lt;p&gt;Several students have recently asked me for advice about time management. When people ask you a important and difficult question like this, usually the best thing is to think of someone else who can give a better answer than you. For time management, an obvious person to turn to is the late Randy Pausch, a noted computer scientist who became an internet sensation because of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cmu.edu/randyslecture/book/&quot;&gt;an inspirational lecture&lt;/a&gt; that he gave after he had been diagnosed with terminal cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I’d like to recommend a different, more practical, and excellent lecture that he gave on time management:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oTugjssqOT0&quot;&gt;Video of Randy Pausch’s lecture on time management&lt;/a&gt; (1 hour, 15 minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/Randy/RandyPauschTimeManagement2007.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides of lecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stafforini.com/blog/summary-of-time-management-by-randy-pausch/&quot;&gt;Summary of ‘Time management’, by Randy Pausch&lt;/a&gt;. Bullet points written by Pablo Stafforini.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should start by watching the lecture. I found it helpful to have the slides and bullet points in separate windows on screen as I watched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need further encouragement to watch the lecture, I can say
that what amazed me, as poor at time management as I may be, was the number of suggestions
that I actually use day-to-day. I had entirely forgotten just how much I had learned the first time I saw this material. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find your most creative time of day and defend it ruthlessly. The most important tip that you can learn for creative work. (I was interested to learn later that your most creative time can actually change over the years.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Turn off your email notification sound. Do it now!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Learn ways to say “no” gently. It makes saying “no” easier.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Don’t ever delete emails. Search instead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep a todo list and calendar. My today-self says, “Well, duh.” But there was a time when I didn’t. You should start now!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get a speakerphone so that you can get other things done while on hold with customer serve. Now, mobile phones or even Skype has a speakerphone option that works for this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Professors should keep Kleenex in their office. Yes, we all need this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keeping a clock on the wall behind where your visitors sit. Much less obtrusive than a wristwatch.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Write down one-minute minutes. So helpful! Just the main takeaways and actions for next time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Keep a time clock. A big topic that I hope to write more about later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also an equally long list of good advice that I had forgotten, but for that, you’ll need to watch the lecture yourself!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="time management" /><summary type="html">Several students have recently asked me for advice about time management. When people ask you a important and difficult question like this, usually the best thing is to think of someone else who can give a better answer than you. For time management, an obvious person to turn to is the late Randy Pausch, a noted computer scientist who became an internet sensation because of an inspirational lecture that he gave after he had been diagnosed with terminal cancer.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy Blogoversary to me</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/08/blogoversary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy Blogoversary to me" /><published>2017-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/08/blogoversary</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/08/blogoversary.html">&lt;p&gt;I don’t like to write about the blog on the blog, because that seems silly and self-indulgent, but I can’t help noticing that today is the five year anniversary of &lt;a href=&quot;/2012/08/converting-fahrenheit-into-celsius.html&quot;&gt;my first blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t feel like I’ve been blogging that long. Perhaps that’s because I post only once every few years. If you like the blog (and if you don’t — why would you read a post like this???), you’ll be happy to know that I’ll be posting more often in the coming year. I’ve found a posting rhythm that works for me: write all my posts at once while I’m on holiday, and queue them up for the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy I started doing this. I often mention my posts when my students ask me for advice, which has the benefit that my students get tired of hearing about the blog, and therefore stop wanting to meet with me. This leaves my students with more time to carry out excellent research, while leaving me with more time to play old versions of Minesweeper. Everybody wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any regrets? Perhaps only that I wish I could write more silly posts like &lt;a href=&quot;/2014/02/a-suggestion-for-scotland.html&quot;&gt;my manifesto on the political future of Scotland&lt;/a&gt;, but real-life politics have grown dark enough that I find myself unable to summon the spirit of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even without fun, I have lots of ideas for posts about career advice and about the academic and research enterprises. So this will probably be that kind of blog for a wee while longer. It’s fascinating how the theme and how the tone of a blog evolves. I had some ideas about what the blog would be like when I started, but the more I continued, the more I found the blog grow into something different than I expected. Much like life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I can guarantee (disclaimer: this is not a legal guarantee) is that the blog will continue to be reflective and introspective, and that if you’ve liked it so far, you’ll probably like what’s coming next.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="metablog" /><summary type="html">I don’t like to write about the blog on the blog, because that seems silly and self-indulgent, but I can’t help noticing that today is the five year anniversary of my first blog post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Context switching</title><link href="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/07/context-switching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Context switching" /><published>2017-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-01T13:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/07/context-switching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.theexclusive.org//2017/07/context-switching.html">&lt;p&gt;Of the many quirks shared by computer scientists, one that has somewhat entered the popular culture is the use of computing metaphors to speak about how we think. For example, “multitasking” is actually a technical term invented by computer scientists &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_multitasking&quot;&gt;in the 1960s&lt;/a&gt; to describe the way a computer pretends to execute many programs at once, even if in reality it can only do one thing at a time. You can see why the term would have been quickly co-opted to metaphorically describe humans who attempt the same trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the benefit of the three or four readers of the blog who are not computer scientists, I’ll digress here in order to comment that the situation on the computing side has gotten more complicated since the 60s, as almost all modern computers can perform many operations at once, but they still use multitasking so that they can pretend to do even more. That probably sounds like some people you know, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professional computer scientists have many more metaphors at their command, though. We speak of “swapping in” and “swapping out” the details of a project from our short-term memories, referring to a technique that allows computers to pretend to have infinitely large memories. We also — and now I come finally to the topic of the post — talk about “context switching”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A context switch is a necessary result of multitasking. If a computer is pretending to run ten programs at once when it can in reality run only one, then it must switch very quickly back and forth between them, like a chef switching between stirring the sauce and browning the meat. Unlike the chef, on a computer the switching comes with a price. The price comes because computers have many different types of memory, some fast and close to the CPU, others larger and farther away.  Every time the computer switches from one program to another, it has to move data about the old program out of the small fast memory, and move the new data in. The work of switching back and forth is what we call context switching. It takes a bit of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is in your mind. When you switch between different tasks, it takes a while to remember the other context: what it was that you were supposed to be doing on the new task, why you thought it was a good idea, and so on. This is why you’re not as efficient when you first start a new task as when you’ve been thinking about it for a while. This has led to the deluge of self-help articles, some of which I’m sure you’ve seen, about how mental multitasking is a bad idea. It takes time to switch contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a professor &lt;small&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theexclusive.org/2013/08/academic-ranks-in-us-and-uk.html&quot;&gt;in the US sense&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/small&gt;, especially leading a research group, context switching cannot be avoided. The nature of the job requires us to make progress on many different types of tasks each day, from answering a student question about a problem set, to planning for the curriculum next year, to reading a paper related to one research project, to an impromptu meeting with a colleague about faculty hiring for next spring, to a scheduled meeting with a PhD student about a different research project. One of my mentors liked to joke, “Professors are stateless” (another computing metaphor). The reason that we seem stateless is that it takes some time for us to remember the previous context. Not only does it take time to context switch, but it is also a bit disorienting. A colleague once told me that the part of being a professor that they disliked the most was having to context switch many times a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People sometimes ask me how I handle context switching. I have a few strategies. One is a bit embarrassing, but I will tell you anyway. Perhaps I made this a long post to drive people away before I revealed the embarrassing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First is not to be afraid to ask questions. This is useful in one-to-one student meetings about a research project. You can say something like: “Sorry, what was the vorpal sort for again?” Of course, if you do this too much, you derail the meeting. But with practice I found that much of the time, simply asking the question silently in my head was enough. Once I had articulated the question clearly, I was able remember the answer, without bothering the student to repeat what we had already discussed. I’m sure this makes me look smarter, but more importantly it saves time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I keep relevant information easy to search on my computer. This is why I am never without my laptop. I don’t try to remember all that I need to know so much as remember how to find it in my email, in my Evernote, by a Web search that I know will bring up a particular page, or whatever. Then if I’m in a large meeting, for example, where I can’t just stop and ask twenty people to remind me what they said in last week’s meeting, I can search quietly and find the context I need.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When I know I’ll need to make a big context switch, I’ll take a break to clear my head. A ten-minute walk helps, or staring out a window, or something sweet. Coffee doesn’t work here for me; it’s great for energy, of course, but not for context switching.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If I write something down, I know down to my unconscious that it’s OK to stop thinking about it, because now I can come back later. When I have meetings back to back, during the second meeting I might remember something I should have said in the first. If I quickly jot down a note, that helps me to stop thinking about the first meeting, and return to the task at hand. This works within meetings too. Sometimes I think of something that I need to say in a one-on-one meeting, but it’s not as important as what we’re talking about right now. I’ll write that down too. I’ll even say something as I’m doing this, so we both know there’s something to come back to later.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OK, OK, I’ll tell you the embarrassing one. I have some mental imagery that I use. I imagine my focus of attention as the beam of light coming from a huge lamp, like at the top of the lighthouse. When I need to switch focus quickly, like between back to back meetings, I imagine myself grasping the lamp between my hands — it’s several feet around, and heavy, so this takes a real effort — and slowly rotating it to shine onto the new problem that I’m meant to be thinking about. Believe it or not, sometimes this works. I will never tell you when I am doing this, even if you ask.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Charles Sutton</name></author><category term="advice" /><category term="how to think" /><category term="stupid brain tricks" /><summary type="html">Of the many quirks shared by computer scientists, one that has somewhat entered the popular culture is the use of computing metaphors to speak about how we think. For example, “multitasking” is actually a technical term invented by computer scientists in the 1960s to describe the way a computer pretends to execute many programs at once, even if in reality it can only do one thing at a time. You can see why the term would have been quickly co-opted to metaphorically describe humans who attempt the same trick.</summary></entry></feed>
